<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The stumbling-stone, or, A discourse touching that offence which the world and worldly church do take against 1. Christ himself. 2. His true word. 3. His true worship. 4. His true church. 5. His true government. 6. His true ministry. Wherein the University is reproved by the Word of God. Delivered partly to the University-congregation in Cambridge, partly to another in the same town. Together with a brief touch in the epistle (for the present) on the late quarrelsom, weak, and erroneous Animadversions of one Mr. Chambers, called Doctor in Divinity, and Pastor of Pewsy in Wiltshire. By William Dell minister of the Gospel, and Master of Gonvil and Cains Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
            <author>Dell, William, d. 1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 148 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D930</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E692_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206987</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866065</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866065</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118325</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82320)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118325)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 107:E692[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The stumbling-stone, or, A discourse touching that offence which the world and worldly church do take against 1. Christ himself. 2. His true word. 3. His true worship. 4. His true church. 5. His true government. 6. His true ministry. Wherein the University is reproved by the Word of God. Delivered partly to the University-congregation in Cambridge, partly to another in the same town. Together with a brief touch in the epistle (for the present) on the late quarrelsom, weak, and erroneous Animadversions of one Mr. Chambers, called Doctor in Divinity, and Pastor of Pewsy in Wiltshire. By William Dell minister of the Gospel, and Master of Gonvil and Cains Colledge in Cambridge.</title>
                  <author>Dell, William, d. 1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.W. for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the Black-spread Eagle at the West end of Pauls.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon on Matt. xi. 6, warning all universities to repent, in reply o Humphrey Chamber's "Animadversions on Mr. William Dells book intituled The crucified and quickned Christian".</note>
                  <note>The words "1. Christ himself. .. 6. His true ministry." are enclosed in brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chambers, Humphrey, 1598 or 9-1662. --  Animadversions on Mr. William Dells book intituled The crucified and quickned Christian.</term>
               <term>Dell, William, d. 1664. --  Crucified and quickened Christian.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Matthew XI, 6 --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Emma (Leeson) Huber</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118325:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Stumbling-Stone, OR, A Diſcourſe touching that offence which the World and Worldly Church do take againſt<list>
                  <item>1. Chriſt Himſelf.</item>
                  <item>2. His true Word.</item>
                  <item>3. His true Worſhip.</item>
                  <item>4. His true Church.</item>
                  <item>5. His true Government.</item>
                  <item>6. His true Miniſtry.</item>
               </list> Wherein the UNIVERSITY is reproved by the WORD of GOD. Delivered partly to the Univerſity-Congregation in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> partly to another in the ſame Town. <hi>Together with</hi> A brief touch in the Epiſtle (for the preſent) on the late quarrelſom, weak, and erroneous Animadverſions of one Mr. <hi>Chambers,</hi> called Doctor in Divinity, and Paſtor of <hi>Pewſy</hi> in <hi>Wiltſhire.</hi> By <hi>William Dell</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel, and Maſter of <hi>Gonvil</hi> and <hi>Caius</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Mihi plane omnium jucundiſſima facies iſta in rebus eſt, videre ob verbum Dei ſtudia &amp; diſſentiones fieri: is enim eſt Verbi Dei curſus, caſus &amp; eventus; nam dicit, non veni pacem mittere ſed gladium. </q>
            <bibl>Luther.</bibl>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R. W.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread <hi>Eagle</hi> at the Weſt end of Pauls. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:118325:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118325:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere I preſent thee with this <hi>Diſcourſe,</hi> which met with ſuch <hi>notable</hi> Oppoſition and Contradiction from the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> to whom it was deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and alſo from ſuch of the <hi>Town</hi> then preſent, who are <hi>baptized</hi> into the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity <hi>ſpirit;</hi> And yet <hi>every</hi> point of this <hi>Doctrine</hi> will appear to <hi>ſpiritual</hi> men, to be the Word and Truth of <hi>God,</hi> and if <hi>need</hi> ſhall require, I can yet more fully prove it to be ſo, by the <hi>Scriptures</hi> of the <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and by the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf the Head of both, and that againſt not only <hi>One,</hi> but <hi>All</hi> Univerſities, and alſo againſt the Gates of Hell and Powers of darkneſs. And by this <hi>groſs</hi> Oppoſition againſt the <hi>plain</hi> Goſpel, thou maiſt judge and diſcern that this <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> which hath beeen counted one of the <hi>Eyes</hi> of the Nation, SEEING SEES NOT; and which hath been counted a <hi>Fountain</hi> of <hi>Knowledge</hi> and <hi>good Learning,</hi> HEARING HEARS NOT, NEITHER UNDERSTANDS; Whereby we may conceive that <hi>gray Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs</hi> are upon it, and that the time of its <hi>departure</hi> is near, except it REPENT.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:118325:3"/>
I had thought alſo at this time to have given a <hi>far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Teſtimony</hi> for <hi>Jeſus,</hi> againſt the <hi>Myſterie of iniquity</hi> which hath hitherto prevailed in the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical State,</hi> and in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> the Head and Heart of it, but that this work under my hands, multiplied into too <hi>great</hi> a Proportion for an <hi>Epiſtle;</hi> And alſo becauſe I intend to add threunto my <hi>Teſtimony</hi> againſt that <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of Iniquity</hi> which hath hitherto alſo prevailed in the <hi>civilState,</hi> Antichriſt having with his deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs, ſeduced and deluded <hi>both</hi> ever ſince the Reign of <hi>Conſtantine;</hi> And this <hi>twofold Teſtimonie,</hi> (through Grace given and hoped to be given) I intend very ſhortly to publiſh; For I Judge it moſt neceſſary for the <hi>true Church</hi> to be acquainted herewith, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after ſo many of the <hi>Seals</hi> have been opened, and alſo ſeeing the time of the <hi>Reſtitution of all things</hi> makes haſte upon us, and we hope is even at the doors. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we continually intreat that the <hi>Arm</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> would <hi>awaken</hi> and put on <hi>ſtrength,</hi> not only as in <hi>Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent</hi> times, and in the days of <hi>old,</hi> but <hi>more</hi> alſo, to wit, as his <hi>Spirit</hi> by his <hi>Prophets</hi> hath foretold he will do in the <hi>laſt time,</hi> when he will reveal his Arm for Chriſt and his ſeed, in his <hi>greateſt</hi> Might and Glory: And let the <hi>Remembrancers</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> not keep ſilence, till the <hi>curſed Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> with all its Religion, Works, Duties, Doctrines, counterfeit Law and Goſpel, falſe Clergy, falſe Church, falſe Power and Juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or Diſcipline, falſe Ordinances, and falſe all things, be utterly <hi>overcome</hi> with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſts mouth,</hi> and the <hi>Brightneſs</hi> of his coming; And till the true <hi>ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Church,</hi> that through Faith, Hope, and Love, lives out of this <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Elements</hi> thereof, in the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of Gods dear <hi>Son</hi> be made an <hi>Eternal Excellency,</hi> and the <hi>Ioy of Generations;</hi> and till they who have <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118325:3"/>
it, and <hi>domineered</hi> over it, be made to come humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>bending</hi> to it, and to lick the <hi>duſt</hi> of its <hi>feet,</hi> as the <hi>Lord</hi> hath promiſed.</p>
            <p>Farther, I thought good at this time to advertiſe thee of the <hi>Animadverſions</hi> of Mr. <hi>Humfry Chambers,</hi> called Doctor in Divinity, and Paſtor of <hi>Pewſy</hi> in the County of <hi>Wilts,</hi> on a diſcourſe publiſhed by me, enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>The Crucified and quickned Chriſtian.</hi> In which <hi>Animadverſions</hi> (as he calls them; after Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Loves</hi> Example, who was one of his <hi>Forerunners</hi> in this oppoſition to the Truth) he hath <hi>Doctor-like,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted the <hi>manifeſt Truth,</hi> and the very <hi>Subſtance, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> and <hi>Myſterie</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which being made <hi>void</hi> (which yet is <hi>impoſsible</hi> as to the true Church) there would be neither true Righteouſneſs, nor Life, nor Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, nor Salvation, nor the true Chriſt, nor the true God in Chriſt left <hi>remaining</hi> to Believers; <hi>All</hi> which I make account in <hi>due</hi> time to make appear by the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> (for I allow no <hi>Doctrine</hi> that is not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording <note place="margin">Chriſt is the only Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver, and the Spirit is the only Law In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter.</note> to the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the writings of his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> which are a moſt <hi>ſure</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible word,</hi> if they be underſtood according to <hi>Chriſts</hi> mind, and not according to <hi>Mans.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when I read thoſe <hi>Animadverſions,</hi> I found them very <hi>Captious, Slight, Weak,</hi> and groſly <hi>erroneous,</hi> and ſomewhat like the Animadverſions of the <hi>Sorbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> on ſome of <hi>Luthers</hi> writings; And this hath not been my Judgement only, but alſo it hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to me from <hi>godly</hi> and <hi>underſtanding</hi> Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that this great undertaking of this <hi>Doctor</hi> is judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>ſuch</hi> by them, that it deſerves no more <hi>Refutation;</hi> his <hi>Animadverſions</hi> compared only with the <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> it ſelf, being ſufficiently for ever already confuted by it. And truly I cannot but <hi>bleſs</hi> God, who hath given
<pb facs="tcp:118325:4"/>
his <hi>Truth</hi> ſo weak an <hi>Enemy,</hi> and <hi>Error</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs</hi> ſo weak a <hi>Patron.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But by this the <hi>true Church</hi> may judge alſo, what a <hi>ſad Miniſtry</hi> theſe poor <hi>Nations</hi> have received from <hi>Antichriſts Ordination,</hi> when the <hi>chief Doctors,</hi> the very <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> among the <hi>Clergy,</hi> do not know the very <hi>firſt Principles</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> in any <hi>ſpiritual light,</hi> or by any <hi>Teaching</hi> from <hi>God,</hi> but all their cold, faint, and uncertain. Doctrine they ſcrape from <hi>Fathers,</hi> and <hi>Schoolmen,</hi> and from other <hi>Ordinary Syſtemes</hi> of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity,</hi> without any <hi>preſence</hi> of Faith, or <hi>anointing of</hi> the Spirit, whereby all their <hi>Doctrine</hi> becomes <hi>carnal,</hi> and <hi>corrupt,</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> to Chriſts mind, and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Antichriſts; So that I cannot chooſe but <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude</hi> with <hi>John Hus,</hi> THAT ALL THE CLERGY MUST BE QUITE TAKEN AVVAY ERE THE <note place="margin">Ioan. Hus libr. de vita &amp; Reg. Antichriſt. cap. 37.</note> CHURCH OF CHRIST CAN HAVE ANY TRUE REFORMATION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Another</hi> thing hath happened in this <hi>matter,</hi> which makes me <hi>wonder,</hi> and that is, that thoſe few <hi>Shreds</hi> of weakneſs and Error publiſhed by <hi>Mr. Chambers,</hi> ſhould be ſo <hi>honourably</hi> licenſed by ſo <hi>famous</hi> a Divine, as the preſent <hi>Vicechancellor</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> a man of ſuch excellent <note place="margin">Mr. Owen.</note> Learning and Judgement; But truly ſuch Doctrine deſerved ſuch a Licenſe, that ſomething at leaſt might make it <hi>conſiderable;</hi> Whereas the <hi>true Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>Word of Faith,</hi> the <hi>Word of the Kingdom,</hi> hath a <hi>ſtanding Licenſe</hi> from Jeſus Chriſt, and comes upon the World as the <hi>Rain</hi> and <hi>Dew,</hi> without asking <note place="margin">Prodiit ex adipe iniquitas eorum, tranſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum cordis.</note> 
               <hi>leave</hi> of <hi>Man</hi> or the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>Man.</hi> But <hi>great Places</hi> are greatly <hi>dangerous</hi> to thoſe whoſe Faith is not ſtronger then their <hi>form;</hi> And ſo I leave this alſo to the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Judgement of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, into whoſe hands God hath given all things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:118325:4"/>
Chriſtian, acquaint thy ſelf much with the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and be much in the <hi>prayer</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> for <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>Angels</hi> are preparing to ſound the <hi>Laſt Trumpets,</hi> and to pour out the <hi>Laſt Vials</hi> on the very <hi>Seat</hi> and <hi>Throne</hi> of the <hi>Beaſt;</hi> and we hope ere long, to hear that <hi>ſhout</hi> of <hi>Triumph</hi> in the Spiritual Church, <hi>Babylon is faln, is faln, is faln,</hi> and is now become the <hi>Habitation of Devils,</hi> and <hi>unclean Spirits,</hi> which before was the <hi>Habitation of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites,</hi> and <hi>falſe Chriſtians,</hi> yet <hi>covered</hi> over with all the moſt <hi>glorious</hi> ſhews of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> that the <hi>Deceiveableneſs of Vnrighteouſneſs</hi> could put upon them. And now (if thou pleaſe) read on, and let the <hi>Spiritual man judge, who judgeth all things.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Dell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:118325:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118325:5"/>
            <head>The ſtumbling Stone.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Math. 11. ver. 6.</bibl>
               <q>And bleſſed is he whoſoever ſhall not be offended in me.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are the <hi>concluſion</hi> of Chriſts <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> to that <hi>Queſtion</hi> which <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohns</hi> Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> propounded to him by two of his <hi>Diſciples,</hi> himſelf being in priſon: the <hi>Queſtion</hi> was this, <hi>Art thou he that ſhould come, or do we look for another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now it is much <hi>diſputed,</hi> whether <hi>John</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Some ſay, <hi>Iohn</hi> did not ask it for his own ſake;</note> 
               <hi>himſelf</hi> did at this time <hi>doubt</hi> of Chriſt or no? and ſeveral <hi>men</hi> give in ſeveral <hi>Opinions,</hi> which I ſhall not now ſtand to recite: but <hi>all</hi> almoſt, both <hi>Antient</hi> and <hi>Modern,</hi> do conclude, that <hi>John</hi> propounded this Queſtion to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> not that he <hi>himſelf</hi> did now doubt whether <hi>Chriſt</hi> were the true <hi>Meſſias</hi> or no, ſeeing <hi>He</hi> had before given ſo clear a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> to Chriſt, that he was <hi>the Lamb of God that takes away the ſins of the world,</hi> and had alſo <hi>Baptized</hi> him with water, and had ſeen at that time <hi>the Heavens opening, and the Spirit of God as a Dove deſcending and reſting on Chriſt,</hi> and had heard the <hi>Fathers</hi> own voice, ſaying, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed:</hi> Wherefore <hi>they</hi> ſay, that <hi>John himſelf</hi> could not <hi>poſſibly</hi> after all this, <hi>doubt</hi> of Chriſt; and therefore that he did not propound this <hi>Queſtion</hi> to him by his Diſciples <note place="margin">But for his Diſciples.</note>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118325:6"/>
for his <hi>own</hi> ſake, but for <hi>Theirs,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> who before had <hi>envied Chriſt</hi> for their <hi>Maſters</hi> ſake, and would rather have had <hi>John</hi> to have been the <hi>Meſſias</hi> then <hi>him,</hi> might now be <hi>aſſured</hi> and fully <hi>inſtructed</hi> touching <hi>Chriſt,</hi> from <hi>Chriſt Himſelf:</hi> Thus they.</p>
            <p>But for my part, I do conceive that <hi>Iohn</hi> did propound this <note place="margin">The Authors judgement.</note> Queſtion to <hi>Chriſt</hi> for his <hi>own</hi> ſake rather then for his <hi>Diſciples:</hi> For though when he lived in <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>freedom</hi> he had a clear <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> from the <hi>Father</hi> touching the <hi>Son</hi> by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> and had accordingly cleerly <hi>ſpoken</hi> of Chriſt to <hi>others,</hi> yet now being in <hi>Priſon</hi> and <hi>Bonds,</hi> and neer unto <hi>death,</hi> he is brought by great <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation</hi> and <hi>Temptation,</hi> to <hi>doubt</hi> of all that Truth which <hi>before</hi> he had been taught of <hi>God,</hi> and even to <hi>queſtion</hi> whether <hi>Chriſt were the true Chriſt or no?</hi> For thought he, If he be the <hi>true Chriſt,</hi> why doth he not ſend Redemption to <hi>me,</hi> who ſuffer for <hi>his</hi> ſake, but ſuffer me thus to <hi>periſh,</hi> whilſt he might <hi>help</hi> me, if he be <hi>the</hi> Chriſt? and if he work <hi>Miracles</hi> for <hi>others</hi> (as I hear he doth) why doth he wholly neglect <hi>me,</hi> who have given ſuch an <hi>honourable</hi> Teſtimony to the world of him?</p>
            <p>And truly, <hi>(brethren)</hi> we know not vvhat <hi>place</hi> or <hi>power</hi> the <note place="margin">Tribulation our trial.</note> Goſpel of <hi>God</hi> our <hi>Saviour</hi> hath in us, till <hi>Tribulation</hi> come: and ſo much of the true <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of true <hi>faith</hi> in Chriſt we have <hi>indeed,</hi> as we have <hi>ſtrength</hi> in ſuch hours. <hi>That</hi> truth which we confeſs freely in <hi>Proſperity,</hi> we are fain to begin to <hi>learn</hi> it again in <hi>Tribulation:</hi> and <hi>Tribulation</hi> makes us learn the <hi>Truth</hi> over again the <hi>ſecond time:</hi> it makes us to learn that in <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience,</hi> which before we had learned only in <hi>Doctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And how <hi>hard</hi> a matter it is to <hi>hold faſt</hi> in Trouble, <hi>that</hi> Truth <note place="margin">Hard to hold faſt truth in Trouble.</note> which we well <hi>know</hi> and freely <hi>profeſs</hi> in <hi>Proſperity,</hi> we may ſee, not only in <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> (who being in <hi>Priſon,</hi> doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Chriſt</hi> were the <hi>true</hi> Chriſt, after he had been ſo <hi>clearly</hi> taught him, by <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Spirit,</hi> and had ſo plainly <hi>confeſſed</hi> him) but alſo in the <hi>Diſciples</hi> of Chriſt, who though they had <hi>heard</hi> all his <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>ſeen</hi> all his <hi>works,</hi> and had <hi>confeſſed</hi> him to be <hi>Chriſt the Son of the living God,</hi> yet when the <hi>High-Prieſts</hi> were inraged, and the <hi>People</hi> in an uproar, and when they beheld the <hi>Swords</hi> and the <hi>Staves,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> was apprehended, and <hi>themſelves</hi> in danger, they were <hi>all offended</hi> at him and <hi>fled.</hi> Yea, we may ſee it in <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, who though the <hi>Father</hi> had teſtified touching him three times from Heaven; ſaying, <hi>this is my beloved Son,</hi> &amp;c. Yet
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118325:6"/>
when his <hi>ſuffering</hi> drew near, he exceedingly <hi>feared,</hi> and was <hi>ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi> and <hi>aſtoniſhed,</hi> and on the <hi>Croſs</hi> cried out aloud, <hi>my God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> My <hi>brethren,</hi> no man knows the <hi>grievouſneſs</hi> and <hi>efficacy</hi> of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, and the <hi>weakneſs</hi> and <hi>frailty</hi> of Humane Nature, but they who have had <hi>experience</hi> of both: but this is the comfort of the faithfull, that <hi>that</hi> knowledge of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath taught us, and we have heard and learned from <hi>him,</hi> will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>endure</hi> and <hi>hold out</hi> throughout all the <hi>greateſt</hi> and <hi>longeſt</hi> ſtorms of <hi>Tribulation</hi> and <hi>Temptation,</hi> though with much <hi>ſtriving</hi> and <hi>difficulty:</hi> but <hi>they</hi> who have had much <hi>knowledge</hi> of the Truth, and have made a <hi>glorious profeſſion</hi> of it before <hi>men,</hi> and yet have wanted the <hi>true</hi> Teaching of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>true faith</hi> through that teaching, <hi>ſuch</hi> when <hi>Tribulations</hi> and <hi>Difficulties</hi> have riſen up, have quite <hi>departed</hi> from the <hi>Truth,</hi> and have often <hi>renounced</hi> it.</p>
            <p>We <hi>know</hi> not brethren (I ſay again) what we do <hi>believe</hi> aright, touching <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel,</hi> touching the <hi>Love</hi> of God to us, and the <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of our ſin, &amp;c. till <hi>diſtreſs,</hi> and <hi>Tribulation</hi> and <hi>death</hi> come; and <hi>what</hi> we are <hi>then,</hi> we are that <hi>indeed;</hi> Yea, at <hi>ſuch</hi> times, we are to be judged according to our <hi>faith,</hi> and not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our <hi>ſenſe</hi> and <hi>feeling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Luther</hi> was wont to ſay, that in <hi>Temptation</hi> he could <hi>hardly</hi> make <note place="margin">Luther.</note> uſe at all of that <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>free Grace of God to ſinners,</hi> and of <hi>faith in Chriſt crucified, &amp;c.</hi> which at <hi>other</hi> times he did preach in much <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>utterance.</hi> And he ſaid <hi>another</hi> time, That if he were addicted to <hi>Gods</hi> word at <hi>all</hi> times alike, and could find ſuch <hi>love</hi> and <hi>deſire</hi> thereto in his heart <hi>alwayes,</hi> as he did <hi>ſometimes,</hi> he ſhould reckon himſelf the <hi>happieſt</hi> man in the world.</p>
            <p>Now from all theſe things I <hi>conclude,</hi> that <hi>John</hi> being in <hi>Priſon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Concluſion of this.</note> and being fallen into many <hi>Tribulations</hi> and <hi>Temptations,</hi> did ſend theſe two Diſciples unto <hi>Chriſt</hi> for his <hi>own</hi> cauſe, and for his <hi>own</hi> confirmation, as it is ſaid <hi>ver.</hi> 2. and 3.</p>
            <p>Ver. 2. <hi>When Iohn had heard in priſon the works of Chriſt, he ſent two of his Diſciples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 3. <hi>And ſaid unto him, Art thou he that ſhould come, or do we look for another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:118325:7"/>
Whence we are farther to <hi>obſerve,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> That <hi>Iohn</hi> in his doubting ſends to <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and would not turn aſide to the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> to take <hi>advice</hi> from them, or to demand their <hi>judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>true faith,</hi> in all <hi>doubtings</hi> touching Chriſt, goes to Chriſt <hi>himſelf</hi> for <hi>Reſolution,</hi> and will be <hi>ſatisfied</hi> from <hi>none</hi> but from <note place="margin">Faith asks of Chriſt.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Chriſt</hi> is as ready to ſatisfie <hi>Iohn,</hi> as <hi>Iohn</hi> to inquire and ask; and ſo <hi>he</hi> returns him this <hi>Anſwer</hi> by his Diſciples. <note place="margin">Chriſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers faith.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 4. <hi>Go and ſhew Iohn again thoſe things you ſee and hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ver. 5. <hi>The blind receive their ſight, and the lame walk; the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers are clenſed, and the deaf hear; the dead are raiſed up, and the poor have the Goſpel preached to them:</hi> and now let <hi>Iohn</hi> himſelf re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve his <hi>own</hi> Queſtion, <hi>whether I am the true Chriſt or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Go ſhew Iohn the things you ſee and hear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where you ſee, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth not ſay in <hi>plain terms</hi> that he was the <hi>Chriſt;</hi> yea he often <hi>forbade</hi> men to ſay ſo; but he would <note place="margin">Chriſt, how known?</note> have his <hi>Works</hi> and his <hi>Word</hi> declare what he was, that our <hi>faith</hi> might have a <hi>ſure foundation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Chriſt would be known by his Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The blind receive their ſight, the lame walk, &amp;c.</hi> and ſo every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where <note place="margin">1. Chriſt known by his works. 1. In himſelf the Head.</note> in the Goſpel, <hi>Chriſt</hi> would be <hi>known</hi> to be what he <hi>was,</hi> by his <hi>Works<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> particularly in <hi>Ioh.</hi> 10. 24. when the Jews came round about him, and ſaid, <hi>How long doſt thou make us doubt? if thou be the Chriſt, tell us plainly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Jeſus thus anſwered them, ver. 25. <hi>I told you, and ye believed not; the works that I do in my Fathers name they bear witneſs of me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ver. 37. 38. he ſaith to them, <hi>If I do not the works of my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, believe me not; But if I do, though ye believe not me, believe the works, that ye may know and believe that the father is in me, and I in him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you ſee, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> will be known to be what he is by his <hi>Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Power, Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God, is a moſt <hi>lively</hi> and <hi>active</hi> Principle, and cannot lie <hi>hid</hi> where he is <hi>preſent</hi> and <hi>dwels;</hi> but when <hi>this</hi> Word was <hi>made fleſh.</hi> i. e. <hi>came</hi> into the fleſh, it did <hi>manifeſt</hi> it ſelf to be in that <hi>fleſh,</hi> by doing the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118325:7"/>
               <hi>works</hi> of God; and <hi>without</hi> the works of God the <hi>preſence</hi> of the <hi>eternal word</hi> in the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> had not been <hi>known.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſt is called <hi>God manifeſted in the fleſh,</hi> and not <hi>hidden;</hi> and he was manifeſt to be <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>fleſh,</hi> by doing the <hi>works</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>And as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is known by his works, in <hi>himſelf</hi> the <hi>Head,</hi> ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <note place="margin">2. In the Church his body.</note> in the <hi>Church</hi> his <hi>Body:</hi> for whereever Chriſts <hi>Preſence</hi> is, there alſo are his <hi>Works;</hi> and where his <hi>Works</hi> are not, there neither is his <hi>Preſence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If <hi>Chriſt</hi> be preſent in our <hi>hearts</hi> by <hi>faith,</hi> his Works will be undoubtedly manifeſt in our <hi>lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> Now if any ſhall ſay, <hi>But it is not neceſſary for every Chriſtian to do the Works of Chriſt here mentioned,</hi> to wit, to <hi>cauſe the blind to ſee, and the lame to walk, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, yet <hi>howeever</hi> there are <hi>other</hi> Works of <hi>Chriſt</hi> beſides theſe, which are <hi>inſeparable</hi> from his preſence, as the <hi>work of faith,</hi> and <hi>labor of love,</hi> and <hi>patience of hope,</hi> together with the <hi>ſelfdenial</hi> of Chriſt, the <hi>Meekneſs, Lowlineſs, Goodneſs, Long ſuffering, Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-mindedneſs</hi> of Chriſt; as alſo his readineſs and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ligence to <hi>do</hi> the will of God, and his cheerfulneſs to <hi>ſuffer</hi> it; <hi>theſe</hi> works (I ſay) <hi>every one</hi> ought to perform, that is a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> that ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> may ſtill be known by his <hi>works,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>Shew me thy faith by thy works,</hi> that is, let me know the <hi>preſence</hi> of Chriſt in thee, by the <hi>works</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And thus is <hi>Chriſt</hi> known by his <hi>works,</hi> both in <hi>Himſelf</hi> and in his <hi>Members.</hi> And thus much touching the Works of Chriſt in general.</p>
            <p>Now for the <hi>kinde</hi> of the <hi>Works</hi> which <hi>Chriſt</hi> did, as, to <hi>give</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Kinde of Chriſts works.</note> 
               <hi>eyes to the blind,</hi> and <hi>ſtrength to the lame,</hi> &amp;c. it is to be <hi>noted,</hi> that they <hi>all</hi> are <hi>ſuch</hi> works as the <hi>Prophets</hi> had foretold the <hi>Meſſias</hi> ſhould perform when he came into the world, as <hi>Iſai. 35. ver.</hi> 5. Behold God will come and ſave you; <hi>Then the eyes of the blind ſhall be opened, and the ears of the deaf that be unſtopped; then ſhall the lame man leap as an hart, and the tongue of the dumb ſing:</hi> and <hi>He</hi> that <hi>did</hi> theſe things, thus foretold by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> muſt needs be the <hi>true Chriſt:</hi> and <hi>theſe</hi> works were a demonſtration of the <hi>efficacy</hi> of his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth here deſcribe <hi>himſelf</hi> by his own <hi>proper</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom lies with the afflicted.</note> 
               <hi>works,</hi> as one whoſe <hi>buſineſs, imployment</hi> and <hi>Kingdom</hi> lies with
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118325:8"/>
the Poor, Lame, Blind, and all ſorts of Diſeaſed, Afflicted, Sorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and diſtreſſed perſons; and theſe <hi>poor creatures</hi> he doth not neglect and deſpiſe, but his <hi>proper Office</hi> is among <hi>theſe,</hi> and theſe he comprehends in the <hi>greateſt love,</hi> and pitties with the <hi>tendereſt bowels,</hi> and minds and tends with the <hi>greateſt care</hi> and diligence, and relieves, and helps, and ſaves them perfectly.</p>
            <p>Whence firſt we learn, That Chriſts Kingdom <hi>brings</hi> good to <note place="margin">Chriſts King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom brings good to all.</note> 
               <hi>all,</hi> but it <hi>receives</hi> nothing from <hi>any body;</hi> For it carries in it all the <hi>unſearchable Riches</hi> of God, and ſtands in <hi>need</hi> of nothing that <hi>man</hi> can do. Wherefore it entertains not the <hi>rich,</hi> and <hi>full,</hi> &amp; <hi>noble,</hi> and <hi>honourable</hi> of the world, and ſuch as <hi>abound</hi> already, and have <hi>enough</hi> in themſelves and the creatures; but only the <hi>poor,</hi> and <hi>needy,</hi> and <hi>afflicted,</hi> and deſolate, and it <hi>ſupplies</hi> theſe freely and richly, and ſends the other <hi>empty</hi> away. And this is the <hi>true Nature</hi> of Chriſts Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Seeing <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>proper</hi> Office hath only to do <note place="margin">Nothing but goodneſs in Chriſt.</note> with the <hi>poor</hi> and <hi>afflicted</hi> people, we may learn to make a <hi>right judgement</hi> of Chriſt, that is, that our <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> is ſuch a <hi>ſweet</hi> Saviour, that in him is <hi>nothing</hi> but love, and <hi>mercy,</hi> and <hi>goodneſs,</hi> and compaſſion, and kindneſs to ſuch as are in <hi>diſtreſs,</hi> and in grievous <hi>fears</hi> and <hi>agonies</hi> from the ſenſe of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>wrath,</hi> and from the preſence of <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> working in them. And we muſt <hi>believe</hi> Chriſt to be <hi>ſuch</hi> an one as the <hi>Goſpel</hi> repreſents him, that we may <hi>come</hi> to him with comfort, and put our whole <hi>truſt</hi> in him, in all times of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſorrow,</hi> and in all hours of <hi>darkneſs,</hi> and <hi>temptation:</hi> and let us never <hi>entertain</hi> any other thoughts of <hi>Chriſt</hi> then theſe, but let us hold him <hi>unchangeably</hi> for <hi>ſuch</hi> an one as the Goſpel <hi>reveals</hi> him, what ever the <hi>Law,</hi> or our <hi>evil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> or the <hi>Devil</hi> ſhall ſuggeſt to the contrary; and then in all our <hi>diſtreſſes</hi> we ſhall not be <hi>affraid</hi> of Chriſt as of a ſevere <hi>Lawgiver,</hi> and an unexorable <hi>Iudge,</hi> but may run to him as to our mercifull and powerfull <hi>Saviour,</hi> whoſe <hi>proper Office</hi> is among the <hi>afflicted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we ſee that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is known by his <hi>Works,</hi> and what <hi>kinde</hi> of works they are.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Chriſt would be known by his Word.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. Chriſt known by his Word.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is known by his <hi>Works,</hi> ſo alſo by his <hi>Word,</hi> and therefore he ſaith, <hi>Go ſhew Iohn the things you ſee and hear;</hi> and the things you <hi>hear</hi> as well as the things you <hi>ſee,</hi> and that is, that <hi>the poor have the Goſpel preached to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118325:8"/>
For Chriſts <hi>works</hi> and Chriſts <hi>Word</hi> do alwayes <hi>go together.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſts works and word go always toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> Chriſts <hi>Life</hi> is alwayes accompanied with Chriſts <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and his <hi>works</hi> with his <hi>Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>beſt works</hi> that any man can do, without the <hi>word</hi> of the Goſpel <hi>accompanying</hi> them, are not <hi>Chriſts</hi> Works; and the moſt <hi>glorius word</hi> that any man can hold forth, without the <hi>works</hi> of Chriſt <hi>accompanying</hi> it, is not <hi>Chriſts</hi> word: but <hi>Chriſts works</hi> and <hi>Chriſts word</hi> go alwayes <hi>together,</hi> both in <hi>himſelf</hi> the <hi>Head,</hi> and in the <hi>true Church</hi> his <hi>body:</hi> Wherefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Go ſhew to Iohn the things you ſee, and hear:</hi> the things you <hi>ſee;</hi> the <hi>blind receive their ſight, &amp;c.</hi> the things you <hi>hear;</hi> and the <hi>poor have the Goſpel preached to them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is the free <hi>promiſe</hi> of God, in which <hi>nothing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Goſpel, what it is.</note> but <hi>meer</hi> love, mercy and grace is offered in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> to them that <hi>believe,</hi> though they be never ſo great and grievous <hi>Sinners</hi> in themſelves. And nothing is more <hi>joyfull</hi> then <hi>this</hi> to the ſoul that is under the ſenſe of <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>wrath:</hi> and he that <hi>receives</hi> this Word of <hi>Grace</hi> by true <hi>faith,</hi> doth not weigh a feather all the <hi>terrors</hi> of the Law, Sin, Death and Hell. So that all the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward works</hi> of Chriſt are a <hi>ſmall matter,</hi> if compared to the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Goſpel</hi> is preached to the <hi>Poor,</hi> that is, to the <hi>Poor in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">It is preached to the poor.</note> 
               <hi>Spirit;</hi> and theſe are <hi>ſuch,</hi> who do not love, nor deſire, nor delight in <hi>preſent</hi> things, but are ſo <hi>afflicted</hi> and <hi>oppreſſed</hi> in their heart &amp; conſciences with the ſenſe of <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>wrath,</hi> that they <hi>regard</hi> not the <hi>world,</hi> nor the <hi>Riches, Pleaſures,</hi> and <hi>Honors</hi> of it, but <hi>all</hi> they mind, or care for, is <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and in <hi>Him,</hi> the <hi>love</hi> of God, and the <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of ſin, and the gift of the <hi>Spirit. Theſe</hi> are the <hi>Poor</hi> to whom Chriſt <hi>Preaches</hi> the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and they <hi>only</hi> regard and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> whil'ſt the <hi>Lovers</hi> of this <hi>world,</hi> and the Lovers of <hi>themſelves</hi> and this <hi>preſent</hi> life, <hi>care</hi> not for it.</p>
            <p>And thus is <hi>Chriſt</hi> known, by preaching the <hi>Goſpel</hi> to the <hi>poor.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſt known by the Goſpel as <hi>Moſes</hi> by the Law.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> his Miniſtry was full of wrath, terror, and death to <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners;</hi> but <hi>Chriſts</hi> miniſtry holds forth nothing to the <hi>greateſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> in the world, that are <hi>ſenſible</hi> of ſin, but the <hi>free Grace</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of God to <hi>them,</hi> even to <hi>them,</hi> in <hi>pardoning</hi> their ſin, and <note place="margin">Chriſt known by the Word in the Church his body, aſwel as in himſelf the Head.</note> giving them <hi>righteouſneſs;</hi> and by <hi>this word</hi> Chriſt is well known, to the whole <hi>true</hi> Church of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is known by his <hi>Word</hi> in himſelf the <hi>Head,</hi> ſo alſo in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118325:9"/>
the <hi>Church</hi> his <hi>Body;</hi> for whereever <hi>Chriſt</hi> is preſent, there is his <hi>Word,</hi> aſwell as his <hi>works;</hi> and where Chriſts true <hi>Word</hi> is not, neither is his <hi>preſence</hi> there. Wherefore <hi>all</hi> the <hi>faithfull,</hi> as they have received the <hi>Goſpel</hi> themſelves, ſo they hold forth the <hi>ſame</hi> Goſpel to <hi>others,</hi> upon all opportunities, according to the <hi>Covenant</hi> which God made with <hi>Chriſt</hi> touching his <hi>Seed,</hi> which is mentioned <hi>Iſa. 51. ver. 21. As for me, this is my Covenant with them, ſaith the Lord; my Spirit which is upon thee, and the words which I have put into thy mouth</hi> (that is, the Goſpel) <hi>ſhall never depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeeds ſeed, from henceforth and for ever.</hi> By which <hi>Scripture</hi> we may learn, that the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> is a <hi>common</hi> Miniſtry, belonging <hi>equally</hi> and alike to <hi>all</hi> the ſeed of Chriſt, that is, to all <hi>true believers:</hi> for when <hi>Chriſt</hi> dwells in their <hi>hearts</hi> by faith, who ſhall hinder <hi>Chriſt</hi> in them, from <hi>ſpeaking</hi> the Word of God by <hi>them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>God</hi> doth not <hi>conſider</hi> men as the <hi>World</hi> doth, to wit, as they are <hi>Tradeſmen,</hi> or <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> or <hi>Schollars,</hi> or <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> but <note place="margin">God conſiders men either as Believers, or Unbelievers.</note> he conſiders men as <hi>Believers,</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers.</hi> And if they be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believers,</hi> then are they <hi>deſtitute</hi> of the true <hi>preſence</hi> of Chriſt, and of the true <hi>Word</hi> of Chriſt, what ever their <hi>outward</hi> condition be in the <hi>World, yea</hi> though they be <hi>Schollars</hi> and <hi>Clergy-men;</hi> and if they are <hi>Believers,</hi> then have they <hi>Chriſts</hi> true <hi>preſence</hi> and <hi>word</hi> with them, what ever their <hi>outward</hi> condition is in the world, yea though they be <hi>Gentlemen</hi> or <hi>Tradeſmen;</hi> and <hi>every</hi> one of them ſaith with <hi>David</hi> and with <hi>Paul, I believed, therefore have I ſpoken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that we are not to conceive of the <hi>ſpiritual Church</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">The true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry is only of Believers.</note> to any <hi>outward</hi> ſtate or condition in the <hi>world,</hi> but according to <hi>Faith,</hi> through which <hi>Chriſt</hi> dwells in the hearts of <hi>believers;</hi> and if <hi>Chriſt</hi> the living word of God, <hi>dwel</hi> in them, he will not <hi>keep ſilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this <hi>confeſſion</hi> of the <hi>word</hi> before the <hi>world,</hi> Chriſt requires of <hi>all</hi> believers <hi>alike,</hi> ſaying, <hi>He that confeſſeth me before men, him will I confeſs before my father, and before his Angels;</hi> and there is no <hi>true</hi> and <hi>right</hi> confeſſing Chriſt without <hi>holding forth</hi> the word and Doctrine of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, <hi>every</hi> one that is of God, <hi>ſpeaks</hi> Gods <hi>word;</hi> and he that ſpeaks it <hi>not,</hi> is not of <hi>God;</hi> for in all the true <hi>children</hi> of God,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118325:9"/>
the <hi>Spirit of their father ſpeaks in them.</hi> And thus, the true <hi>preſence</hi> of Chriſt is known by the <hi>word</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> in the Church his <hi>body,</hi> and in every one of his <hi>Members</hi> aſwell, as in <hi>himſelf</hi> the <hi>head. This</hi> Doctrine, the <hi>carnal Church</hi> is a great <hi>enemy</hi> to, and <note place="margin">The carnal Church offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at this Doctrine.</note> will not ſuffer <hi>Chriſt</hi> to ſpeak by <hi>whom</hi> he pleaſeth, that ſo <hi>all</hi> men may be <hi>neceſſitated</hi> to hear its <hi>Clergy,</hi> whether they ſpeak the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or no: but of this more hereafter.</p>
            <p>And thus you have ſeen, how <hi>Chriſt</hi> gives forth himſelf to be <hi>known</hi> by his <hi>works</hi> and by his <hi>word;</hi> and without theſe <hi>two</hi> we can have no <hi>certain</hi> Teſtimony of him, in the <hi>world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Chriſt</hi> having returned this full and ſatisfactory <hi>Anſwer</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Chriſts Anſwer to <hi>Iohn.</hi>
               </note> to <hi>Iohn,</hi> to declare to him who he was, adds this in the <hi>conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And bleſſed is he whoſoever ſhall not be offended in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For notwithſtanding the <hi>works</hi> and <hi>word</hi> of Chriſt, which are <note place="margin">The World offended at Chriſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding his works and Word.</note> the works and word of <hi>God in the fleſh,</hi> yet the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> of the fleſh, and the <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the World, which do not much <hi>regard</hi> thoſe things, do finde <hi>much</hi> matter of <hi>ſcandal</hi> and <hi>offenſe</hi> in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> wherefore Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſoever ſhall not be offended in me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now in diſcourſing touching the <hi>Offence,</hi> which is taken againſt <note place="margin">This Offence diſcourſed of.</note> 
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> by <hi>men,</hi> I ſhall obſerve this <hi>Order;</hi> I ſhall ſhew</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Who</hi> they are that are <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>What</hi> thoſe <hi>things</hi> are whereat they are <hi>offended,</hi> and <hi>why</hi> they are offended at them.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>What</hi> a great <hi>evil</hi> it is to be ſo offended.</item>
               <item>4. <hi>What</hi> a great <hi>bleſſednes</hi> it is not to be ſo offended, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <item>5. Make ſome <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of all.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="point">
               <head>1. Point.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who they are that are offended at Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Who offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Chriſt. 1. The whole World.</note>And here I <hi>affirm,</hi> firſt that the <hi>whole world</hi> in general is offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Chriſt; for <hi>they</hi> living without the <hi>word</hi> and <hi>Spirit of faith,</hi> muſt needs be offended at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by all thoſe ſcandals which are raiſed up againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by the <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>men;</hi> and they all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a <hi>falſe</hi> apprehenſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> do ſuck in as readily as a <hi>ſpring</hi> doth <hi>water,</hi> what ever <hi>aſperſions</hi> and <hi>reproaches</hi> are raiſed againſt him, and ſo muſt needs be <hi>offended</hi> at him: and therefore ſaith
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118325:10"/>
Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18 ver. 7. <hi>wo be to the world becauſe of offences;</hi> for <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences</hi> muſt <hi>needs</hi> come, and the <hi>world</hi> will needs <hi>receive</hi> them, and therefore <hi>wo be to the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So that the <hi>whole World,</hi> that is, whoſoever are not <hi>true belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</hi> and <hi>born</hi> of God, are <hi>all</hi> offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his Goſpel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all the <hi>children</hi> of the <hi>firſt Adam</hi> are offended at the <hi>ſecond Adam,</hi> who is wholly <hi>unlike</hi> to them, yea and in <hi>all</hi> things moſt <hi>contrary</hi> to them.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Yea ſecondly, Not only the <hi>common people</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">And herein the chief and choice men of the World.</note> vulgar and contemptible men, are offended at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but alſo all the <hi>chief</hi> and <hi>choice</hi> men of the world, <hi>Kings</hi> of the earth, and <hi>Rulers,</hi> and <hi>Judges,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> as in <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 2. and all the <hi>beſt,</hi> and <hi>learnedſt,</hi> and <hi>wiſeſt,</hi> and <hi>greateſt,</hi> and moſt <hi>honourable</hi> men, theſe <hi>all</hi> are offended at <hi>Chriſt.</hi> 1 Cor. 2. 8. <hi>which none of the Princes of this world knew;</hi> he means it of <hi>Philoſophers</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well as of <hi>ſecular Powers;</hi> and not <hi>knowing</hi> him, they <hi>Crucified</hi> him.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Not the <hi>World</hi> only are offended at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but alſo the <hi>Worldly and carnal Church,</hi> the <hi>Outward, Viſible, National</hi> Church, <note place="margin">2. The World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church.</note> 
                  <hi>this</hi> is very much offended at him. <hi>This</hi> we ſee in <hi>Chriſts</hi> time, that the only <hi>Viſible Church</hi> of God in the World, the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> (for the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Old</hi> Teſtament, was a <hi>Viſible</hi> Church, but the Church of the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament is a <hi>Spiritual</hi> Church, and <hi>not</hi> viſible) I ſay, the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, which had the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> and obſerved all the <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> Ordinances of God <hi>exactly,</hi> they were all <hi>Offended</hi> at Chriſt, and made an <hi>Order</hi> that <hi>whoſoever acknowledged him ſhould be excommunicated,</hi> and caſt out of the Synagogue.</p>
               <p>And this <hi>Offence</hi> was foretold by <hi>Iſai. chap. 8. ver.</hi> 14. where he ſaith of Chriſt, <hi>And he ſhall be for a ſtone of ſtumbling and for a rock of Offence to both Houſes of Iſrael, for a ginne, and for a ſnare to the Inhabitants of Jeruſalem.</hi> So that not <hi>Babylon</hi> only, but <hi>Ieruſalem;</hi> and not the <hi>Heathen</hi> only, but <hi>both</hi> the Houſes of <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> were offended at <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and this makes the <hi>evil</hi> yet more <hi>grievous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet <hi>this</hi> is not <hi>all;</hi> but ſecondly, and not only the <hi>carnal Chriſtians,</hi> but the <hi>carnal Clergy</hi> are offended at <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and not <note place="margin">And herein the Miniſters and chief Rul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</note> only the <hi>common people</hi> of the <hi>National</hi> Church, but the <hi>chief Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> the moſt <hi>eminent,</hi> and in appearance moſt <hi>Godly</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:118325:10"/>
and <hi>Orthodox</hi> of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> are above all <hi>others</hi> moſt grievouſly offended at <hi>Chriſt. This</hi> alſo we ſee done in <hi>Chriſts</hi> time, when the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the People, men of great reputation and renown, for <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> theſe were <hi>chiefly,</hi> and above the <hi>reſt</hi> of the Church, <hi>offended</hi> at Chriſt; and as <hi>Chriſt</hi> everywhere was moſt <hi>ſharp</hi> againſt them, and did moſt <hi>reprove</hi> them; ſo <hi>they</hi> did moſt <hi>bitterly</hi> oppoſe <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And <hi>this</hi> alſo was <hi>foretold</hi> by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Propheſie, Pſalm 118. 22. The ſtone which the Builders refuſed, is become the Head of the corner:</hi> this <hi>rejected ſtone,</hi> is <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf; and theſe <hi>Builders</hi> were the chief <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Governors</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and accordinly both <hi>Chriſt</hi> and the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> applyed this Scripture to <hi>them,</hi> as you may ſee <hi>Mat</hi> 21. 42. and <hi>Act.</hi> 4. 11.</p>
               <p>So that the <hi>Builders,</hi> that teach, and inſtruct, and govern the <hi>Church,</hi> and are reputed the <hi>beſt,</hi> and moſt <hi>profitable</hi> and <hi>neceſſary</hi> men in it, yea the very <hi>Pillars</hi> of the Church, ſo that <hi>all</hi> would come to <hi>nought,</hi> and to <hi>ruine</hi> without them, theſe are the men that are <hi>moſt</hi> offended at <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the <hi>Huſbandmen</hi> mentioned by <hi>Chriſt, Mat.</hi> 21. that conſpired againſt the <hi>Son</hi> of the Lord of the Vineyard, and <hi>killed him;</hi> and <hi>theſe have</hi> been, and ſtill <hi>are,</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Nullus eſt alius Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus in mundo, ne<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> venturus quam Sacerdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. 10. Hus.</hi> By Prieſts he means the Clergy, who challenge to themſelves a proper and ſingular Prieſt-hood diſtinct and apart from other Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> the <hi>chief</hi> and <hi>great</hi> out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward <hi>Antichriſt</hi> in the World.</p>
               <p>Now when the <hi>People</hi> ſee the <hi>Rulers</hi> and <hi>Governors</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> who are <hi>thought</hi> to have more Knowledge, Learning, Light, and Religion then <hi>others,</hi> offended at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> this exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly increaſes <hi>their</hi> Offence; and when <hi>they</hi> ſee the <hi>Builders</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting and throwing away <hi>this Stone,</hi> this cauſes <hi>them</hi> to reject him alſo with the <hi>greater</hi> indignation.</p>
               <p>And thus you ſee that this <hi>Offence</hi> at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is a <hi>great</hi> and a <hi>large evil,</hi> and is ſpread over <hi>all</hi> the World and Worldly Church, and <hi>very few</hi> there are who do <hi>eſcape</hi> it.</p>
               <p>And this for the <hi>firſt</hi> thing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="point">
               <head>2. Point,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>At what things in Chriſt they are Offended, and why they are</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. General, At what offended in Chriſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Offended at them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Worldly Church</hi> are Offended</p>
               <list>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:118325:11"/>
                  <item>1. At <hi>Chriſt</hi> Himſelf.</item>
                  <item>2. At his <hi>true Word.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. At his <hi>true Worſhip.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. At his <hi>true Church.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5. At his <hi>true Miniſtry.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. At his <hi>true Government.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Of <hi>theſe things</hi> I ſhall ſpeak in <hi>Order</hi> according to the <hi>good hand</hi> of God with me, and ſhall <hi>deſire</hi> to be ſo <hi>faithfull</hi> to Chriſt as not to <hi>depart</hi> one hairs breadth from his <hi>truth,</hi> though it may be it will come to paſs that <hi>all</hi> or the <hi>greateſt</hi> part of you will be grievouſly <hi>Offended</hi> at it.</p>
               <p>I begin with the <hi>firſt,</hi> and will ſhew, that the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church</hi> are offended</p>
               <p n="1">1. At <hi>Chriſt Himſelf.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. At Chriſt himſelf, and in him</note>
               </p>
               <p>And they are offended at <hi>him</hi> in many regards, of which I ſhall mention theſe <hi>five.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. They are offended at the <hi>meanneſs</hi> of his <hi>ontward</hi> condition <note place="margin">1. At the Meaneſs of his outward con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the World.</note> in the World. For indeed he was in a very <hi>low, plain, ſimple,</hi> and <hi>contemptible</hi> condition, in the <hi>dayes</hi> of his fleſh, as any <hi>ordinary</hi> Tradeſmen in <hi>this</hi> Town, and lived with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in his <hi>Trade</hi> of a <hi>Carpenter.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of him, <hi>Phil. 2. that he made himſelf of no account, and took upon him the forme of a ſervant, and was made in outward appearance as any other man.</hi> That is, he was in the <hi>outward</hi> condition of any <hi>ordinary</hi> man in the World.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>mean</hi> condition of Chriſt, did much <hi>offend</hi> them; for <hi>thought</hi> they, is this the <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of whom all the <hi>Prophets</hi> have ſpoke ſuch <hi>glorious</hi> things? whom all the <hi>Iews</hi> expect? and who is the <hi>deſire of all Nations?</hi> Is this <hi>He</hi> whoſe name is <hi>wonderfull, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, the mighty God, the everlaſting Father, the Prince of Peace, of the increaſe of whoſe Government and Peace there ſhould be no end, upon the Throne of David, and upon his Kingdom, to order it, and to ſtabliſh it with Juſtice and Judgement from henceforth and for ever?</hi> Is this <hi>plain ordinary</hi> man the <hi>Meſſias?</hi> how can this thing be? For they thought that the <hi>true</hi> Chriſt, of whom ſuch <hi>excellent</hi> things were ſpoken, ſhould be ſome <hi>great Prince</hi> or <hi>learned Prieſt;</hi> and that <hi>that form</hi> of a <hi>ſervant</hi> and <hi>mean</hi> condition in which he was, could in no meaſure <hi>agree</hi> or be <hi>ſutable</hi> to the true <hi>Chriſt;</hi> And for <hi>this</hi> cauſe, they were greatly <hi>offended</hi> at
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118325:11"/>
him, and thought <hi>Him</hi> not <hi>worthy</hi> to be in any place of <hi>reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They were <hi>offended</hi> that he being in ſo <hi>mean</hi> an outward <note place="margin">2. That in ſo low a conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch high things were ſpoken of him.</note> condition, <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſhould yet ſpeak ſuch <hi>high things</hi> of <hi>Him,</hi> and he of <hi>Himſelf. Iohn Baptiſt</hi> teſtified of him, that <hi>he</hi> was the <hi>only begotten Son in the boſome of the Father; the Lamb of God that takes away the ſins of the World;</hi> the <hi>fountain</hi> of the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Saints;</hi> the <hi>beloved Son</hi> unto whoſe hands the <hi>Father</hi> had given <hi>all things;</hi> and that <hi>he that did believe in him, had ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life; and he that did not, ſhould not ſee life, but the wrath of God ſhould abide on him, &amp;c.</hi> and theſe <hi>all</hi> were <hi>wonderfull</hi> things, to be ſpoken of <hi>one</hi> whoſe <hi>outward</hi> condition in the <hi>World</hi> was ſo <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>contemptible.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as <hi>Iohn</hi> had ſpoken theſe things of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where gives forth <hi>himſelf</hi> as the <hi>Son of God,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>He and his Father were one.</hi> And this exceeding <hi>offended</hi> the <hi>Iews,</hi> as you may ſee <hi>Iohn 5. 18. The Iews ſought to kill him, not only becauſe he had broken the Sabbath, but alſo becauſe he had ſaid, God was his Father, making himſelf equal with God.</hi> And <hi>Iohn 10. 31. The Iews took up Stones to Stone him, and ſaid, we Stone thee not for a good work, but for blaſphemy, and becauſe thou being a man makeſt thy ſelf God.</hi> And ſo they were <hi>all</hi> offended at <hi>this</hi> Myſtery, <hi>God manifeſt in the fleſh,</hi> in the <hi>fleſh</hi> of ſo <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>deſpicable</hi> a perſon in the <hi>eye</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They were offended at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> becauſe in <hi>him</hi> was no <hi>humane</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">3. Becauſe in Chriſt was no meerly humane nor carnal thing.</note> or <hi>worldly</hi> thing, which any <hi>Natural</hi> or <hi>Carnal</hi> man could poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>like</hi> of, or <hi>delight</hi> in; He <hi>excerciſed</hi> no <hi>worldly</hi> witt, Wſdom, Reaſon, Learning, Parts, nor <hi>any thing</hi> that might <hi>commend</hi> him to the <hi>World;</hi> neither did he <hi>live</hi> in any outward <hi>formes</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion or Worſhip which might <hi>commend</hi> him to the <hi>carnal Church.</hi> There was <hi>nothing</hi> in <hi>Him</hi> but the <hi>preſence</hi> and <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation</hi> of God, the <hi>Word</hi> of God, the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God, the <hi>Nature</hi> of God, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God, the <hi>Works</hi> of God, and <hi>God</hi> was <hi>all</hi> in <hi>all</hi> in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>God</hi> is wholly <hi>contrary</hi> to the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> And ſo the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> were wholly <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt, He</hi> being altogether in the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Father</hi> in <hi>him,</hi> in ſuch ſort that the <hi>Father</hi> in him <hi>ſpake</hi> all the words, and <hi>did</hi> all the works, and <hi>he</hi> could neither <hi>do</hi> nor <hi>ſpeak</hi> any thing of <hi>himſelf<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> he was taken up, unto ſo <hi>neer</hi> Union and Communion with <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:118325:12"/>
4. They were offended at the <hi>reproaches</hi> and <hi>miſreports</hi> that <note place="margin">4. They were offended at his Reproaches.</note> went commonly abroad touching <hi>Chriſt,</hi> raiſed for the moſt part by the <hi>Scribes,</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> becauſe they <hi>knew</hi> and were <hi>aſſured</hi> that Chriſts <hi>prevailing</hi> would be their <hi>undoing;</hi> Therefore they gave out that he was a <hi>Sabbath-breaker,</hi> a <hi>Blaſphemer,</hi> an <hi>unlearned</hi> and <hi>ignorant</hi> man, and <hi>that</hi> made him err, a <hi>Vitious</hi> man, a <hi>Glutton</hi> and <hi>Winebibber,</hi> a <hi>friend of Publicans and ſinners,</hi> and that he had a <hi>Devil,</hi> and was <hi>mad;</hi> theſe were the <hi>common reports</hi> that were <hi>commonly</hi> divulged abroad touching <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and that by the <hi>Teachers</hi> of the beſt <hi>repute</hi> in the Church; and the <hi>common-people</hi> reckoned them to be very <hi>true,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon were horribly <hi>offended</hi> both at Chriſts <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this was <hi>Chriſt</hi> a very <hi>ſign to be ſpoken againſt,</hi> which <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foreſeeing in the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſpeaks thus in the <hi>perſon</hi> of the <hi>offended</hi> Jewiſh Church, <hi>Iſai. 63. 3. He is deſpiſed and rejected of men, a man of ſorrows and acquainted with grief, and we hid as it were our faces from him; he was deſpiſed and we eſteemed him not.</hi> And <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf by the <hi>Prophet</hi> complains of this <hi>uſage,</hi> ſaying, <hi>they laid to my charge the things that I knew not;</hi> But yet theſe <hi>falſe reports</hi> ſo far <hi>prevailed,</hi> that he became a <hi>Stranger to his brethren, and an Alien to his Mothers own Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. They were <hi>offended</hi> at him becauſe of his <hi>bitter</hi> and <hi>ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full croſs and ſufferings;</hi> and herein lay the <hi>heighth,</hi> and <hi>depth</hi> of that <note place="margin">5. At his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings.</note> Offence for which the <hi>VVorld</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> look at <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Power <hi>condemned</hi> him as a <hi>deceiver,</hi> and <hi>blaſphemer,</hi> and they alſo <hi>prevailed</hi> with the <hi>ſecular</hi> Power to condemn him as a <hi>Seditious perſon,</hi> an <hi>Enemy</hi> to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and a <hi>Rebel;</hi> And ſo after all the <hi>works</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which he had done, and <hi>works</hi> of <hi>God</hi> which he had taught, they at laſt <hi>Crucified</hi> him between two <hi>Thieves</hi> by the <hi>common conſent</hi> of all the People, and <hi>deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> the <hi>Son of God,</hi> as if he had been the <hi>Son of Perdition:</hi> And in all this <hi>bitter ſuffering</hi> no body afforded him the <hi>leaſt</hi> pitty or compaſſion, but the common People <hi>mocked</hi> him, and ſaid, <hi>he ſaved others but cannnot ſave himſelf; if thou be the Son of God, come down from the Croſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this uſage <hi>Chriſt</hi> complains of to his <hi>Father, Pſalm</hi> 22. 6. where he ſaith, <hi>that He by his cries had no deliverance,</hi> which yet <hi>Others</hi> who had <hi>truſted</hi> in God <hi>obtained,</hi> but (ſaith he) <hi>I am a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118325:12"/>
worm, and no man, a reproach of men, and deſpiſed of the People; All they that ſee me laugh me to ſcorn; they ſhout out the lip, they ſhake the head, ſaying, be truſted in God, that he would deliver him, let him deliver him if he delight in him.</hi> And <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith, that by reaſon of this <hi>ſtrange</hi> ſuffering of Chriſt, <hi>many were aſtoniſhed at him, his viſage was marr'd more then any mans, and his face more then the ſons of men;</hi> and through this <hi>ſuffering</hi> of Chriſt, <hi>all</hi> the World were ſo <hi>extreamly</hi> offended, that <hi>Chriſt crucified</hi> was to the <hi>Iews a ſtumbling block, and to the Greeks fooliſhneſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus <hi>was</hi> and <hi>is</hi> the <hi>VVorld</hi> and <hi>Worldly Church</hi> offended at the <hi>true</hi> Chriſt, whom the <hi>Scriptures</hi> hold forth. Indeed the <hi>falſe</hi> Church have <hi>fancied</hi> to themſelves <hi>ſuch</hi> a Chriſt as <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> can like of well enough, a <hi>Chriſt</hi> faſhioned after the <hi>mind</hi> and <hi>will,</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>man,</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> a Chriſt they <hi>extol</hi> and <hi>magnifie,</hi> to wit for their own <hi>worldly</hi> advantage ſake, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have fancied the por <hi>Virgin</hi> his <hi>Mother,</hi> who kept <hi>Ioſephs</hi> houſe, and provided his <hi>diet,</hi> and layd her <hi>hands</hi> to the performance of his <hi>ordinary</hi> houſehold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, to be a <hi>gallant Lady,</hi> and have clothed her in <hi>Silke,</hi> and <hi>Sat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> and rich attire; and ſuch a <hi>Mother</hi> of Chriſt they do <hi>highly</hi> eſteem; whereas the <hi>poor Virgin,</hi> the <hi>true believer,</hi> who lived in the <hi>plain</hi> and <hi>laborious</hi> imployment of a <hi>Family,</hi> they would even <hi>ſcorn</hi> to regard <hi>ſuch</hi> an one: No more will the <hi>carnal Church</hi> regard or value the <hi>true Chriſt</hi> in his <hi>mean</hi> condition and <hi>marred</hi> Viſage.</p>
               <p>And thus much for their <hi>Offenſe</hi> at Chriſt <hi>himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>The World and Worldly Church are offended at Chriſts true</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. They are offended at his his true Word.</note> 
                  <hi>VVord,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> hath given forth a <hi>New VVord,</hi> which is the <hi>VVord of the Goſpel;</hi> And <hi>this</hi> alſo they are <hi>offended</hi> at, in <hi>many</hi> regards; as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe it is the <hi>word of Faith;</hi> the word of <hi>Faith,</hi> and not <note place="margin">1. Becauſe it is the Word of faith.</note> of <hi>Senſe;</hi> the Word of <hi>Faith,</hi> and not of <hi>VVorks.</hi> For this <hi>VVord</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> is wholly a <hi>Spiritual</hi> Word, and hath <hi>nothing</hi> in it that is ſutable to <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>blood;</hi> Nothing in it, that <hi>pleaſeth</hi> the Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or Reaſon, or Underſtanding of man; it hath nothing in it <note place="margin">2. Becauſe it exalts Chriſt alone, and God in Chriſt.</note> wherein a <hi>Natural</hi> or <hi>Carnal</hi> heart can take <hi>pleaſure,</hi> but is <hi>throughout</hi> a Word of <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They are offended at the <hi>New word</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:118325:13"/>
becauſe it exalts <hi>Chriſt alone,</hi> and in him the <hi>Power</hi> of God, and the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of God, and the <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of God, and the <hi>Things</hi> of God; and <hi>cries down</hi> all the Things of the <hi>World</hi> in which men <hi>truſt</hi> and <hi>delight,</hi> and all the common <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of the World, and makes <hi>Chriſt all in all,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> in Chriſt, and <hi>all</hi> other things <hi>nothing.</hi> So <hi>Paul</hi> 1 Cor. 1. preached to them that did believe, <hi>Chriſt the power of God, and Chriſt the wiſdom of God, and nothing elſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They are offended at <hi>this</hi> Word, becauſe it cannot be <hi>learned</hi> as humane <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> can, to wit by the teaching of <hi>man,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">3. Becauſe it can only be learned by the Teaching of God.</note> together with their <hi>own</hi> pains and endeavors, but only by the <hi>teaching of God</hi> and his <hi>Spirit,</hi> as it is written, <hi>They</hi> (that is, the true children of the Spiritual Church) <hi>ſhall be all taught of God; he therefore that hath heard and learned of my father, cometh to me. All my divinity, (ſaid</hi> Luther) <hi>conſiſteth in this, that I believe that Chriſt only is the Lord touching whom the ſcriptures ſpeak, and neither my Grammer nor Hebrew tongue taught me this, but it is the work of the holy ſpirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now when <hi>God</hi> teacheth us his word <hi>Himſelf,</hi> we have an <hi>other</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">When God teacheth us his Word, we know it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then other men.</note> 
                  <hi>underſtanding</hi> of it then <hi>other</hi> men who hear and read the <hi>ſame</hi> outward words, and yet want that <hi>inward Teaching;</hi> For then have we the <hi>ſpiritual</hi> meaning of the <hi>Word,</hi> and the very <hi>mind</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in it, which <hi>others</hi> want, that are not ſo taught; And this offends the <hi>carnal Chriſtians</hi> grievouſly, that the <hi>ſpiritual Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> have <hi>another</hi> knowledge and underſtanding of the <hi>Word</hi> then <hi>they;</hi> VVhereupon they thus break out, what (ſay they) are you the <hi>only</hi> men who have the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and is all wiſdom and knowledge comprehended in <hi>your</hi> breſts? and do <hi>you</hi> know more of the <hi>Myſterie</hi> of of <hi>Chriſt</hi> then the <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> men who have <hi>ſtudied</hi> the Scriptures all their <hi>life?</hi> and will <hi>you</hi> with your <hi>pretended</hi> teaching overthrow that <hi>Orthodox</hi> ſenſe of the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures</hi> that we have had ſo many <hi>yeers?</hi> and thus they are greatly offended.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are offended at this word becauſe it <hi>diſcovers</hi> the <note place="margin">4. Becauſe it diſcovers the wickedneſs of the World, and worldly Church.</note> wickedneſs of the <hi>world</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> at a very <hi>high</hi> rate. The <hi>world</hi> doth not ſeem the <hi>thouſand</hi> part ſo <hi>wicked</hi> anywhere as it doth where the <hi>Goſpel</hi> comes. For where this <hi>cleer light</hi> of God <hi>ſhines,</hi> and the <hi>word</hi> comes in any degree of <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> there not only the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of the <hi>world</hi> appears out of <hi>meaſure</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:118325:13"/>
wicked, but alſo the <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Works,</hi> and <hi>Duties</hi> of the <hi>carnal</hi> Chriſtians, are manifeſted to be <hi>groſs hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> and the <hi>deceivableneſs of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> and wholly <hi>contrary</hi> to Chriſt, the <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> of God, and ſo nothing elſe but a more <hi>plauſible</hi> way to <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of <hi>God</hi> comes in <hi>power,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Many who ſeemed good, are diſcovered to be very evil by the light of the Word.</note> there many who before <hi>ſeemed</hi> very Godly and Religious people, and very good Chriſtians, and very quiet and peaceable men, do preſently <hi>become</hi> full of wrath and rage, and curſed enmity againſt it, and call it <hi>Error,</hi> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and <hi>Blaſphemy,</hi> and ſo do no leſs then <hi>ſpit</hi> in the very <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which he hath manifeſted above all his name: And no man could ever have <hi>imagined</hi> they had been ſuch <hi>children</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> before the word came.</p>
               <p>And thus by the coming of the <hi>Word</hi> in the <hi>Spiritual</hi> Senſe and Doctrine of it, many that did once <hi>ſeem</hi> to be Chriſts <hi>Friends,</hi> are <hi>manifeſted</hi> to be his utter <hi>Enemies.</hi> And this alſo was foretold by <hi>Simeon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Luke 2. Where he ſaith, that by the coming of Chriſt in his word, <hi>the thoughts of many hearts ſhall be revealed,</hi> and then that <hi>unbelief</hi> and <hi>enmity</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that before lay <hi>hid,</hi> is <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered</hi> and brought forth by the <hi>Preaching</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> as we have ſeen <hi>heretofore</hi> and <hi>ſtill</hi> ſee by daily experience; And for <hi>this</hi> cauſe alſo they are <hi>offended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. They are offended at the <hi>true Word,</hi> becauſe everywhere ſo <note place="margin">5. Becauſe ſo few entertain it.</note> 
                  <hi>few</hi> entertain it and embrace it: As when <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf preached, there were <hi>very few</hi> in all <hi>Iudea</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> that entertained his Doctrine; and though <hi>ſometimes</hi> many thronged to hear him, yet at <hi>another</hi> time they were ſo <hi>offended</hi> at his Doctrine, that they all <hi>forſook</hi> him; ſo that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid to the twelve, <hi>Iohn 6. Will ye alſo go away?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this makes <hi>many</hi> to be offended at the <hi>true Word,</hi> that when it comes to any town or people, the far <hi>greater</hi> part ſhould <hi>reject</hi> it, and <hi>ſpeak evil</hi> of it; and they for the moſt part, the <hi>greateſt, wiſeſt,</hi> and <hi>learnedſt</hi> men, and that only a <hi>few</hi> poor and contemptible people ſhould <hi>receive</hi> it; this alſo exceedingly offends.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And <hi>laſtly,</hi> They are <hi>offended</hi> becauſe the <hi>true Word</hi> of Chriſt <note place="margin">6. Becauſe it occaſions troubles.</note> where it comes in any evidence, and demonſtration of the Spirit<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> brings <hi>Troubles, Tumults, Stirs,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>proars</hi> in the VVorld, ac|
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118325:14"/>
to that of <hi>Chriſt; Mat. 10. 34. I came not to ſend peace but a ſword; for I am come to ſet a man at variance againſt his Father, and the daughter againſt her mother, and the daughter in law againſt her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in law.</hi> For the <hi>true word</hi> of Chriſt, is ſuch a <hi>ſword</hi> as cuts in ſunder all <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> relations, and takes away the <hi>peace</hi> of any place where it comes in <hi>power. Chriſt</hi> ſaith alſo, <hi>Luke 12. 49. I am come to ſend fire on the earth, and what will I if it be already kindled?</hi> This <hi>fire</hi> that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſends is the <hi>word,</hi> in the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the <hi>ſpirit,</hi> of which the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaith by the Prophet, <hi>is not my word as fire?</hi> and <hi>this word</hi> comes to <hi>burn</hi> up all the <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt</hi> Manners Faſhions, Cuſtomes; Yea all the <hi>luſts</hi> and <hi>ſins</hi> of the world, and all the <hi>Antichriſtian Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>formes</hi> of <hi>worſhip</hi> in the <hi>outward Church.</hi> And when this <hi>fire</hi> begins to <hi>burn</hi> anywhere, preſently <hi>all</hi> the people are in an <hi>uproar,</hi> and lay all their <hi>heads,</hi> and uſe all their <hi>hands</hi> together to <hi>quench</hi> it.</p>
               <p>So that where-ever the <hi>true word</hi> comes, the <hi>heathen rage, and the people imagine a vain thing; the Kings of the earth ſet themſelves, and the Rulers take councel together againſt it, and ſay, Let us break theſe bonds in ſunder, and caſt away theſe cords from us,</hi> which no fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh and blood, eſpecially the <hi>Rich, Wiſe, Learned, Honourable,</hi> would endure to be bound in.</p>
               <p>Now this <hi>exceedingly</hi> offends; For ſay they, before <hi>this kind</hi> of word came in, <hi>all</hi> things were <hi>better</hi> and more <hi>quiet:</hi> Under <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The world ſay, before the Goſpel came<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> all things were quiet.</note> all things were wel, and in good order; But ſince this <hi>new Doctrine</hi> came in, all things are full of <hi>trouble, miſchief, wars</hi> and <hi>death;</hi> and therefore they reckon <hi>this word</hi> the cauſe of all the <hi>evils</hi> we have and do endure.</p>
               <p>But yet the <hi>cauſe</hi> of all theſe <hi>tumults,</hi> are not truly in the <hi>word,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The word is not properly the cauſe of theſe Tumults, but by acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</note> but in the <hi>world,</hi> and in the <hi>Devil. Chriſt</hi> he will have his <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> to publiſh his <hi>word,</hi> and thereby to gather together his <hi>elect</hi> unto him: now the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> the <hi>Prince</hi> of it, will not <hi>ſuffer</hi> this to be done <hi>quietly,</hi> and <hi>hence</hi> ariſe all tumults. The <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil</hi> who hath the <hi>firſt</hi> poſſeſſion of the <hi>world,</hi> would have all things <hi>quiet,</hi> that he might <hi>keep</hi> his poſſeſſion; but <hi>Chriſt</hi> will not <hi>ſuffer</hi> it to be ſo, but he will have <hi>all</hi> thoſe whom his <hi>Father</hi> hath <hi>given</hi> him, out of the <hi>Devils</hi> poſſeſſion, by the might and efficacy of his <hi>word;</hi> but the <hi>Devil</hi> will not <hi>endure</hi> that this ſhould be done <hi>quiet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly,</hi> but ſtirs us all the <hi>World</hi> againſt the <hi>word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo where ever the <hi>word</hi> comes in <hi>truth,</hi> there are alwayes
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:118325:14"/>
                  <hi>troubles</hi> and <hi>uproares;</hi> but where the <hi>word</hi> is preached, and the <hi>world</hi> is <hi>quiet,</hi> that for <hi>certain</hi> is not the <hi>true word</hi> of God.</p>
               <p>Wherefore the <hi>dull</hi> and <hi>drouſie</hi> Divinity of <hi>Synods,</hi> and <hi>Schools,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The ordinary Divinity of the Schools is none of Chriſts Word.</note> cannot be the <hi>true word</hi> of Chriſt, for <hi>that</hi> meets with no <hi>oppoſition</hi> and <hi>contradiction</hi> at all from the <hi>World,</hi> or <hi>worldly</hi> Church; it meets with no <hi>enemies,</hi> and <hi>avengers</hi> amongſt them, but it is rather <hi>praiſed</hi> and <hi>embraced,</hi> and honoured with <hi>degrees</hi> and <hi>Scarlet,</hi> and the Profeſſors and Publiſhers of it are in <hi>credit</hi> with men, and <hi>worldly</hi> Powers, and receive from them, <hi>riches, honour,</hi> and <hi>quiet</hi> life; whereas the <hi>true Doctrine</hi> of Chriſt can never be <hi>publiſhed</hi> without the <hi>offence</hi> of the world.</p>
               <p>And thus much for their <hi>offence</hi> at the <hi>true word</hi> of Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>They are offended at his true Worſhip.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">3. At his true Worſhip.</note>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> hath inſtituted a <hi>New-Worſhip,</hi> and this the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly</hi> Church are alſo greatly <hi>offended</hi> at.</p>
               <p>Becauſe <hi>this Worſhip</hi> is wholly <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> and hath nothing <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Becauſe it is Spiritual.</hi> De inſtituendo cultu notanda eſt haec regula, Sine Spiritu Sancto non eſt ſuſcipienda ulla ratio, aut modus colendi Dei. <hi>Luther in c. 35. Gen.</hi> Cultus Dei principaliter &amp; vere conſiſtit non in externis operibus, ſed in fide, ſpe &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectione Dei. <hi>Luth. in cap. 25. Gen.</hi>
                  </note> in it, but conſiſts altogether of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> according to that of <hi>Chriſt, Ioh. 4. 23. The hour cometh</hi> (ſaith He) <hi>and now is, that the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit, and in Truth; For the Father ſeeketh ſuch to worſhip him; God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in Spirit and in Truth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> and there is no worſhip in <hi>truth,</hi> but that which is in <hi>Spirit.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of true believers, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3. 2. we are the <hi>Circumciſion, who worſhip God in the Spirit, and have no confidence in the fleſh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now this <hi>ſpiritual</hi> VVorſhip, ſtands in <hi>Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> whereby our <hi>old</hi> nature is <hi>mortified,</hi> and we bring forth <hi>ſpiritual</hi> fruit unto <hi>God,</hi> and to our <hi>brother.</hi> And <hi>this Worſhip</hi> of the <hi>New-Teſtament</hi> being wholly <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> is free from <hi>Time, Place,</hi> and <hi>Perſon,</hi> as all <hi>ſpiritual</hi> things are; and ſo at <hi>all times,</hi> and in <hi>all places</hi> alike, <hi>this</hi> worſhip may be performed by <hi>all perſons</hi> alike, who are <hi>true believers;</hi> And ſo accordingly do <hi>all</hi> true believers, at <hi>all</hi> times, and in <hi>all</hi> places <hi>alike believe</hi> in God, and <hi>truſt</hi> in him, and <hi>fear</hi> him, and <hi>love</hi> him, and <hi>delight</hi> in him, and <hi>ſpeak</hi> good of his name and alſo <hi>do good</hi> to their <hi>brother,</hi> in Inſtructing, Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Exhorting, Comforting him, and Helping him as <hi>freely</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath helped them; And this is the chief and indeed the only <hi>true</hi> VVorſhip of the <hi>New-Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>Goſpel</hi> hath taught us that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>trueTemple,</hi> wherein
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118325:15"/>
the <hi>Church</hi> of the New-Teſtament, which is a <hi>Kingdom of Prieſts,</hi> are <hi>all</hi> alike to <hi>Worſhip God</hi> without any <hi>difference,</hi> or <hi>diſtinction</hi> of <hi>perſons:</hi> And alſo that Chriſt is our <hi>Reſt</hi> aſwell as our <hi>Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;</hi> and it is as <hi>great</hi> a <hi>ſin</hi> to make another Reſt then <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as it is to make <hi>another</hi> Righteouſneſs then <hi>Chriſt;</hi> For in <hi>him</hi> alone we are <hi>compleat</hi> and furniſhed, to <hi>all</hi> things that appertain to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> And ſtand in need of <hi>nothing</hi> out of him: Wherefore it is ſaid, <hi>Heb. 4. 3. He which hath believed is entred into the reſt,</hi> that is, into <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> and ſo hath <hi>ceaſed from his own works, as God did from his.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly</hi> Church are greatly offended at this <note place="margin">And becauſe this Spiritual worſhip, makes no great ſhew.</note> 
                  <hi>Spiritual Worſhip;</hi> And that firſt, becauſe it makes no <hi>great ſhew,</hi> nor preſents no <hi>glorious outſide</hi> to the <hi>World,</hi> to win their <hi>favour</hi> and applauſe, and ſo they <hi>deſpiſe</hi> it as a <hi>Notional</hi> or <hi>Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> thing.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, becauſe this is <hi>wholly,</hi> out of the <hi>reach</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Natural</hi> man, and no man by his <hi>free will,</hi> or <hi>Natural abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">And alſo is out of the reach of the Natural man.</note> can attain thereunto. VVherefore they are <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>this kind</hi> of VVorſhip, and would have a <hi>Worſhip</hi> in the dayes of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> after the manner of the <hi>VVorſhip</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> a <hi>Worſhip</hi> ſtanding in <hi>outward</hi> works, and Duties, and Ceremonies, and in <hi>Obſervation</hi> of Dayes, Times, Places, Perſons; And are much <hi>ſcandalized</hi> at <hi>that</hi> Worſhip, which ſtands only in <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> and makes <hi>void</hi> all other things.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>They are offended at the true Church of Chriſt.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">4. At the true Church of Chriſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> hath ſet upon a <hi>New-Church,</hi> which is not <hi>outward</hi> and <hi>viſible</hi> as the Church of the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> was; Neither carries in it any <hi>worldly</hi> Pompe, Power, and Glory, as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> doth, but it is wholly <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>inviſible,</hi> and as utterly unknown to the <hi>World</hi> as <hi>Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>true Church</hi> under the <hi>New-Law</hi> is the Congregation of <hi>ſpiritual</hi> men, gathered together, not in <hi>one</hi> outward <hi>place,</hi> but in <note place="margin">What the true Church is.</note> 
                  <hi>one Faith, Hope,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> in one <hi>Spirit,</hi> in one <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in one <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is the company of the <hi>faithful,</hi> and <hi>elect,</hi> which have <hi>Chriſt</hi> for their <hi>Head.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>this</hi> Church is not <hi>known</hi> by any outward <hi>Orders</hi> or <hi>Forms,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">It is known only by the Word of faith.</note> or <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> or manner of <hi>life,</hi> but only by the <hi>Word of Faith;</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:118325:15"/>
ſeeing this true <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Church is conceived and formed, is brought forth, and brought up, is fed and clothed, is ſtrengthned and adorned, is protected and perfected by this <hi>word</hi> of <hi>faith</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; Yea the <hi>whole</hi> Nature, and <hi>life,</hi> and being, and action of <hi>this</hi> Church, is in the <hi>word of faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They are offended at <hi>this</hi> Church becauſe it is the <hi>habitation</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and his very <hi>Kingdom,</hi> wherein he <hi>himſelf</hi> is preſent, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, <note place="margin">2. Becauſe this Church is the Habitation of God.</note> ſpeaks, works, reignes, is glorified, and is <hi>all in all</hi> in it; And ſo it will not <hi>receive</hi> unto it ſelf any thing of the <hi>Power, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> of <hi>Man.</hi> They are much <hi>offended</hi> to hear that <hi>this</hi> Church is the <hi>Temple of the living God,</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> hath ſaid it himſelf, <hi>that he will dwell in them and walk in them:</hi> And that <hi>God is in them of a Truth,</hi> and not by fancied habits of creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed grace: And that <hi>they are filled with all the fulneſs of God:</hi> And that they are <hi>living Stones</hi> in that <hi>Building,</hi> wherein <hi>Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> is the <hi>chief corner</hi> Stone, and that they are <hi>all</hi> built together by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> to be <hi>the Habitation of God:</hi> This doth ſo <hi>exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly</hi> offend them, that is, cauſeth them to <hi>Blaſphem,</hi> in crying out againſt this <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> of God as <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They are <hi>offended</hi> at this <hi>New Church</hi> of the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">3. Becauſe it wil be the true Church alone.</note> becauſe <hi>it</hi> will be the Church of God <hi>alone,</hi> and will not acknowledge <hi>any</hi> to be <hi>of it</hi> but <hi>ſuch</hi> as are <hi>born of God,</hi> and have obtained like <hi>pretious faith</hi> with them: And ſo will have no <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> communion with <hi>any,</hi> (how <hi>skilful</hi> ſoever in the <hi>letter</hi> of the word, and how <hi>eminent</hi> ſo ever in <hi>outward formes</hi> of Religion) but only with <hi>ſuch</hi> who have <hi>true fellowſhip with the Father and the Son</hi> in the <hi>Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. They are <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>this</hi> Church becauſe <hi>uſually</hi> God calls unto it, not the <hi>Great,</hi> and <hi>Honourable,</hi> and <hi>Wiſe,</hi> and <hi>Learned,</hi> but <note place="margin">4. Becauſe it conſiſts of mean people.</note> 
                  <hi>mean, plain,</hi> and <hi>ſimple people,</hi> according to that of <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Cor. 1. 26. <hi>You ſee your calling brethren, how that not many wiſe men after the fleſh, not many mighty, not many noble are called; But God hath choſen the fooliſh things of the world to confound the wiſe, and God hath choſen the weak things of the world to confound the mighty, and baſe things of the world and things which are deſpiſed hath God choſen; Yea &amp; things that are not, to bring to nought things that are.</hi> So that this <hi>true</hi> Church conſiſts of a ſmal company of <hi>Poor, Mean, Simple, Baſe</hi> and deſpiſed men in the eyes of the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:118325:16"/>
Church;</hi> Yea of <hi>ſuch,</hi> who in <hi>their</hi> judgement deſerve to have no <hi>place</hi> nor <hi>being</hi> in the World; And who now out of their own choice would willingly <hi>joyn</hi> themſelves to <hi>ſuch</hi> a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
               <p n="5">5. The <hi>great</hi> and <hi>worldly wiſe</hi> people are much offended at <hi>this</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">5. Becauſe of its outward af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Church, becauſe of its outward <hi>afflicted condition</hi> in the World, it having <hi>fellowſhip</hi> with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in all his <hi>ſufferings;</hi> And ſo is alwayes Reproached, Deſpiſed, Slandered, Torn, Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t on, Buffeted, Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, and Mocked; And from <hi>all, moſt,</hi> or <hi>ſome</hi> of theſe <hi>ſufferings,</hi> the <hi>ſpiritual Church</hi> is never <hi>priviledged</hi> in the World: And by reaſon of <hi>theſe</hi> things, the <hi>viſage</hi> of the <hi>true</hi> Church ſeems <hi>foul de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed,</hi> and <hi>offenſive</hi> in the eys of <hi>men,</hi> whilſt the <hi>national</hi> and <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church</hi> is highly favoured, eſteemed, and preferred <hi>it ſelf,</hi> and hath its <hi>chief Teachers</hi> honoured with <hi>Scarlet,</hi> and <hi>Furrs;</hi> So that if <hi>Chriſt</hi> were on the <hi>earth</hi> again, in his <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>plain condition, He</hi> would be <hi>aſhamed</hi> to own <hi>Them,</hi> and <hi>They</hi> would be as much <note place="margin">5. At the true Government of the Church. 1. Becauſe Chriſt will force none but perſwade all.</note> aſhamed to own <hi>Him.</hi> And thus much for their <hi>offence</hi> at the <hi>true Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>They are offended at the true Government of this Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as he hath ſet up a <hi>New Church,</hi> ſo alſo he hath ſet up a <hi>New Government</hi> of this <hi>Church;</hi> and this alſo <hi>offends</hi> in many regards.</p>
               <p n="1">1. In that <hi>Chriſt</hi> will have none brought to <hi>his</hi> Church, by <hi>out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">In toto Novo Teſtamento, non ſunt praecepta urgentia, ſed tantum exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tationes &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrationes. Nec Chriſtus nec Apoſtoli quenquam un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam coege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt: &amp; Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus fanctus vocatur in hoc Spiritus Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cletus, ut exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetur. <hi>Luth.</hi> 2. Reſponſo ad libr. Amber. Cathar. 2. <hi>Becauſe an Equality in his Kingdom.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>violence,</hi> and <hi>compulſion,</hi> though he have <hi>all Power in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in Earth;</hi> But in the day of his <hi>Power,</hi> (that is, of the <hi>Goſpel,)</hi> he only entertains the <hi>willing People,</hi> and compells no body againſt their <hi>wills;</hi> ſeeing he ſeeks not <hi>his</hi> own <hi>profit,</hi> but <hi>ours.</hi> Our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> gathers his <hi>true</hi> Church on <hi>Earth,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the <hi>Councel</hi> and <hi>Mind</hi> of his Father in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and ſo will <hi>entertain</hi> none but whom his Father <hi>draws,</hi> becauſe he will have <hi>his</hi> Church not one jot <hi>larger</hi> then the <hi>Election</hi> of <hi>Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They are offended at his <hi>Government,</hi> in that in his <hi>true</hi> Church he makes an <hi>equality</hi> between all Chriſtians through <hi>Faith;</hi> and will have none <hi>over</hi> one another, but will have <hi>all</hi> to <hi>ſerve</hi> one another in <hi>Love:</hi> And ſo he will have him that would be the <hi>greateſt,</hi> to be the <hi>leaſt</hi> of all; and him that would be the <hi>chief,</hi> to be the <hi>ſervant</hi> of all, as <hi>Himſelf</hi> came not <hi>to be ſerved, but to ſerve, and to give his life a ranſome for many:</hi> And <hi>He</hi> was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118325:16"/>
                  <hi>greater</hi> then <hi>all</hi> the children of God, not through any <hi>worldly Greatneſs, Lordlineſs,</hi> or <hi>Dominion,</hi> but through his <hi>teaching,</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing</hi> them, and <hi>loving</hi> them, and <hi>ſerving</hi> them, and <hi>ſuffering,</hi> and <hi>dying</hi> for them: And beſides <hi>this</hi> Greatneſs, there is nothing but <hi>Equality</hi> in his Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are offended at <hi>his</hi> Government, in that <hi>Chriſt</hi> doth <note place="margin">3. Becauſe he doth all by his Word and Spirit only.</note> nothing in <hi>his</hi> Church, by the <hi>Decrees</hi> or <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> of <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal men,</hi> or by the <hi>ſecular Arm,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of the <hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> but he doth <hi>all</hi> by his <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> and nothing elſe: And theſe <hi>alone,</hi> without the <hi>addition</hi> of any thing elſe, are <hi>infinitely ſufficient,</hi> to do all that <hi>Chriſt</hi> would have done in his <hi>Kingdom.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">4. Becauſe he will have us only to avoid hereticks and not to harm them.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. In that he will have <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s to love our Enemies, and to do good to them that do evil to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s, and to pray for them that perſecute <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s and deſpitefully uſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s;</hi> He will not have us to be <hi>Enemies</hi> to <hi>any,</hi> or to do evil to <hi>any,</hi> or to perſecute and uſe deſpite to <hi>any:</hi> He will have us to <hi>beware</hi> of <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> but not to <hi>deſtroy</hi> them; And to <hi>avoid</hi> Hereticks, but not to kill them; And will have <hi>neither</hi> of them <hi>burnt</hi> with any <hi>fire,</hi> but the <hi>fire</hi> of <note n="*" place="margin">Igne Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis combu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendi ſunt haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tici, &amp; quicun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> impiè ſapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt &amp; docent. <hi>Luth. Tom. 2. 5. Will have al done by the Law of Love only.</hi> In Novo Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duntur omnia, quae facienda o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittenda<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſunt, ſed nemo cogitur; omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus permittitur ut vel pereant, vel ſalvi fiant. <hi>Luth. Reſpon. ad Ambroſ. Cathar. 6 At his true Miniſtry. This Miniſtry made only by the Unction of the Spirit.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. In that He will have <hi>all</hi> things in his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ordered and done only by the <hi>Law of Love,</hi> and nothing by any <hi>Law of Violence</hi> or <hi>Compulſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>this</hi> kind of <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>true</hi> Church, doth grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly offend the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> and the Governors of <hi>both;</hi> becauſe <hi>They</hi> know no <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> at all, but that of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> and <hi>Civil Power</hi> intermingled, and if <hi>this</hi> be made <hi>void,</hi> they can do nothing at all in the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church, but think according to their <hi>unbelife, all things</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently will come to <hi>Confuſion;</hi> For they want <hi>Faith</hi> to commit the <hi>Government</hi> of Chriſts <hi>own</hi> Church to his own <hi>care;</hi> by his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit.</hi> And thus they are <hi>offended</hi> at this <hi>true Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p n="6">6. And Laſtly (for I will name no more particulars at this time.)</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>They are offended at Chriſts true Miniſtry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> under the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> hath erected and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted a <hi>New Miniſtry,</hi> not through any <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Ordination,</hi> but meeerly through the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction of his Spirit,</hi> without any <hi>Regard</hi> at all to a mans <hi>outward</hi> calling or condition in the <hi>World,</hi> but whether (as I ſaid before) a man be a <hi>Schollar,</hi> or <hi>Clergy man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118325:17"/>
                  <hi>Gentleman,</hi> or <hi>Tradeſman,</hi> if <hi>Chriſt</hi> call him, and pour forth his <hi>Spirit</hi> on him, <hi>that,</hi> and <hi>that only</hi> makes him a <hi>true Miniſter</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of this <hi>New</hi> and <hi>Offenſive Miniſtry</hi> to the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly Church,</hi> Chriſt <hi>himſelf</hi> was the <hi>firſt.</hi> For he was not of <note place="margin">Chriſt himſelf the firſt of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</note> the <hi>tribe of Levi,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. but of the <hi>tribe of Judah, of which Moſes ſpeaks nothing touching Prieſthood:</hi> how then did <hi>Chriſt become the firſt</hi> and <hi>chief Miniſter</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament?</hi> The <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells us by <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 61. and <hi>Chriſt himſe</hi> tells us <hi>Luke</hi> 4. ſaying, <hi>The Spirit of the Lord is upon me; for he hath annointed me to preach the Goſpel to the poor, to preach good tidings to the meek, to bind up the broken-hearted,</hi> &amp;c. So that our Lord <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> being (according to the <hi>Dialect</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt)</hi> a <hi>Lay-man,</hi> and having never <hi>learned Lettters,</hi> nor been brought up a <hi>Scholar,</hi> but being brought up with <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the trade of a <hi>Carpenter,</hi> and not <hi>ordained</hi> neitheir by the <hi>Church</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> nor <hi>allowed</hi> by them, was yet the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>chief Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> of the New Teſtament, through the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction of the Spirit</hi> only.</p>
               <p>Now the <hi>worldly Church</hi> were extreamly <hi>offended</hi> at this <hi>very</hi> thing, as you may ſee in the <hi>Goſpel, Mat. 13. ver. 54. 55. Ieſus came into his own country, and taught them in the Synagogue, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that they were aſtoniſhed,</hi> (for no man ſpake like him, for he taught with Authority, and not as the Scribes) <hi>but they ſaid, whence hath this man</hi> (this Mechanick man) <hi>this wiſdom, and theſe mighty works? is not this the Carpenters Son? Is not his mother called Mary? And are not his brethren and Siſters all with us? and they were offended in him:</hi> that ſuch a man that had no <hi>Degrees,</hi> nor <hi>Ordination,</hi> ſhould yet be a <hi>Miniſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> was the <hi>firſt</hi> Miniſter of <hi>this ſort,</hi> ſo he choſe <hi>others</hi> in the ſame manner: He choſe <hi>Fiſhermen,</hi> and <hi>Tent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">He choſe others like himſelf.</note> and <hi>Publicans,</hi> plain men, and of ordinary imployment in the world, and <hi>only</hi> put his <hi>Spirit</hi> on them, and this was their <hi>ſufficient <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> to the Miniſtry. And thus it was <hi>foretold</hi> by <hi>Ioel,</hi> chap. 2. ver. 28. <hi>And it ſhall come to paſs in the laſt dayes ſaith the Lord, that I will pour out of my Spirit on all fleſh, and your ſons and daughters ſhall propheſie.</hi> There needs <hi>nothing</hi> to the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> but only Gods <hi>pouring out his Spirit:</hi> Wherefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> bids his <hi>Diſciples</hi> ſtay at Jeruſalem till they
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:118325:17"/>
ſhould receive the <hi>promiſe of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>then</hi> they ſhould go forth and <hi>Teach.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo after, as <hi>Believers</hi> received the <hi>Spirit,</hi> ſo they became <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> as we ſee in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,</hi> and in the firſt 300. years after <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For there is but <hi>one only Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> which is <hi>common</hi> to all men <hi>alike</hi> who have received the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> and to <hi>none</hi> elſe, though never ſo <hi>excellently</hi> qualified with <hi>Natural Abilities</hi> and <hi>Humane Learning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the <hi>things</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> are altogether <hi>inviſible</hi> things, and <note place="margin">The things of the Goſpel cannot be known but by the teaching of the Spirit.</note> cannot be <hi>known</hi> but by the <hi>teaching</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> though a man have all the <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Knowledge</hi> in the World, as <hi>Paul</hi> declares 1 <hi>Cor. 2. ver. 8, 9, 10. Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard, nor the Heart of man underſtood the things which God hath prepared for them that love him; but God hath revealed them to <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> (believers) <hi>by the Spirit; for the Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God. For what man knoweth the things of a man, but the ſpirit of a man that is in him? even ſo the things of God knoweth no man but the Spirit of God. Now we have received, not the Spirit of the World</hi> (which for its <hi>higheſt perfection</hi> hath only <hi>humane Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Knowledge) but the Spirit which is of God, that we might know the things that are freely given to us of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where we <hi>learn</hi> that the <hi>things</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> are not <hi>known</hi> at all, nor <hi>diſcerned</hi> in the leaſt meaſure, but by <hi>Gods Spirit;</hi> which <hi>Spirit</hi> is given to <hi>all</hi> that <hi>believe,</hi> and this <hi>Spirit alone</hi> is <hi>ſufficient,</hi> both to enable us to <hi>know</hi> clearly and certainly the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and alſo to <hi>publiſh</hi> them unto <hi>others,</hi> and <hi>nothing</hi> of Man or the Creature can add to it.</p>
               <p>Wherefore when <hi>Chriſt</hi> choſe his <hi>Miniſters</hi> according to his <hi>Fathers</hi> Councel, he choſe not the <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Learned,</hi> but <hi>plain, ſimple</hi> men; that it might <hi>appear</hi> to all the <hi>World,</hi> throughout all <hi>ages,</hi> how <hi>infinitely able</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> of his <hi>Spirit</hi> alone is, without any <hi>addition</hi> of any thing elſe, for the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> upon the <hi>ſerious</hi> conſideration of this <hi>ſtrange choice</hi> of God by Him, breaks forth into this <hi>Thankſgiving, Mat. 11. 25. I thank thee Father Lord of Heaven and Earth, that thou haſt hid theſe things</hi> (that is, the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom) from the Wiſe and Prudent, and haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed them to babes; even ſo Father becauſe it pleaſed thee.</hi> And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118325:18"/>
                  <hi>David</hi> admiring this <hi>wonderfull</hi> diſpenſation, ſpeaks thus in the <hi>joy</hi> of his heart, <hi>Pſal. 8. ver. 1, 2. O Lord our Lord, how excellent is thy Name in all the World, who haſt ſet thy Glory above the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens!</hi> and then ſhowing wherein this <hi>high Glory</hi> of God appears, ſaith, <hi>Out of the mouth of babes and ſucklings haſt thou ordained ſtrength, becauſe of thine enemies, that thou mighteſt ſtill the enemy and the avenger. God</hi> uſeth no <hi>other</hi> Inſtrument to overcome the greateſt <hi>Enemies</hi> and <hi>Avengers,</hi> that ariſe in the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Church,</hi> then the <hi>ſtrength</hi> he ordaines out of the mouths of <hi>babes</hi> and <hi>ſucklings,</hi> that is <hi>true believers,</hi> who live only on the ſincere <hi>milke</hi> of the <hi>Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Lord</hi> had <hi>all</hi> the World before him, to have <hi>choſen</hi> out of it whom he <hi>pleaſed</hi> to be the <hi>Inſtruments</hi> by whom he would hold forth his <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Goſpel</hi> to all Nations; Yet in his infinite <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and gracious <hi>Councel,</hi> and good <hi>Pleaſure,</hi> he would paſs by the <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Learned</hi> men, and great <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> and ſubtile <hi>Diſputants,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> affirms 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 19. that <hi>God</hi> hath ſaid, <hi>I will deſtroy the Wiſdom of the Wiſe, and bring to nothing the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Prudent.</hi> God is ſo far from <hi>making uſe</hi> of Humane Wiſdom, and Prudence in the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of his Son, that he quite <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes</hi> it, and brings it to <hi>nothing:</hi> Wherefore <hi>Paul</hi> adds v. 20. <hi>Where is the wiſe? where is the learned, or lettered man? where is the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſputer of this world? hath not God made fooliſh the wiſdom of this world? For after that in the wiſdom of God, the world by wiſdom knew not God, it pleaſed God by the fooliſhneſs of Preaching to ſave them that believe.</hi> By the <hi>fooliſhneſs of preaching,</hi> that is, by the <hi>Word of Faith</hi> out of the mouth of <hi>Babes</hi> and <hi>Sucklings,</hi> which the <hi>World</hi> reckons <hi>fooliſhneſs:</hi> by this <hi>alone,</hi> doth God bring about the <hi>Salvation</hi> of the Elect.</p>
               <p>Now at <hi>theſe</hi> things how grievouſly are the <hi>Worldly wiſe,</hi> and <hi>deep learned</hi> ones (as they eſteem themſelves) offended? that Gods Spirit <hi>alone</hi> ſhould be a <hi>ſufficient <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction</hi> for the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> and that <hi>God</hi> ſhould on <hi>ſet purpoſe</hi> lay aſide the <hi>Wiſe</hi> and <hi>Prudent</hi> men, and chooſe <hi>babes,</hi> and out of <hi>their</hi> mouth ordain his <hi>great ſtrength</hi> to ſet up <hi>Chriſts</hi> Kingdom in the world, and to deſtroy <hi>Antichriſts?</hi> Yea <hi>this</hi> Doctrine will chiefly of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the <note n="*" place="margin">Univerſity <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd all in it of all Degrees. <hi>Objection</hi> By the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For you will ſay; <hi>If this be ſo,</hi> What <hi>need</hi> is there then of our <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and of our <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> to the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118325:18"/>
                  <hi>New Teſtament?</hi> And what need is there of our <hi>Acts</hi> and Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ums? And what need is there of our <hi>Scarlet,</hi> and <hi>Tippets?</hi> And what need is there of our <hi>Hoods</hi> and <hi>Caps, &amp;c.</hi> If the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> alone be <hi>ſufficient</hi> for the <hi>right Miniſtry,</hi> and Chriſt do <hi>perfect</hi> his praiſe by the <hi>mouths of Babes and ſucklings,</hi> then what need is there of all theſe things?</p>
               <p>I <hi>Anſwer, No need at all,</hi> as to <hi>Chriſts Kingdom,</hi> and the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Anſwer to it.</note> of that: For it is <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>groſſeſt errors</hi> that ever reigned under <hi>Antichriſts</hi> Kingdom, to affirm that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities are the fountain of the Minſters of the Goſpel,</hi> which do only proceed out <note place="margin">Quò indubiè taxat Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias in quibus tales homines creantur, è qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus prodicrunt omnes in orbem praedicatores &amp;c. Totus enim orbis in hac ſententia eſt, hos fontes eſſe, è quibus ſcatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riant qui docere populum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beant. Hic eſt error horrendus &amp; abominan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, ut nihil aeque averſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dumulla ex re, quam ex Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demiis prodie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp;c. <hi>Luth. in loc.</hi> Objection.</note> of <hi>Chriſts flock.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And becauſe you will be <hi>greatly</hi> offended at <hi>me</hi> for ſpeaking thus, you ſhall hear what <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith to <hi>this</hi> matter on 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 1. upon theſe words, <hi>but there were falſe Prophets among the people, as there ſhall be falſe Teachers among you;</hi> the word <hi>Peter</hi> uſes here, is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>falſe Doctors,</hi> or <hi>falſe Maſters;</hi> and <hi>Luther</hi> ſaith it came to paſs by the <hi>ſingular Councel</hi> of God, that our <hi>Teachers</hi> ſhould be called <hi>Doctors and Maſters,</hi> that it my <hi>appear</hi> to all, whom <hi>Peter</hi> here <hi>means:</hi> and he farther ſaith, <hi>that Peter hereby doth undoubtedly tax the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, in which ſuch men are creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and out of which have proceeded all the Preachers in the World, ſo that there is no Town or City under the whole Kingdom of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, which hath not ſuch Doctors and Maſters as are Created in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities. For the whole world</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is of this Opinion, that the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities are the fountains whence they ſhould flow who ought to teach the People. Now this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is a moſt horrible and abominable error, ſo that nothing hath proceeded in all the world, out of any thing, ſo much to be oppoſed, as out of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities: wherefore</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Peter ſaith that all theſe are falſe Maſters, and falſe Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors.</hi> Thus <hi>Luther.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if any ſay, <hi>This Doctrine being commonly taught and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, will throw down the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I <hi>anſwer.</hi> If th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> will ſtand upon an <hi>Humane</hi> and <note place="margin">Anſwer.</note> 
                  <hi>Civil account,</hi> as <hi>Schools</hi> of good <hi>Learning</hi> for the inſtructing and educating Youth in the knowledge of the <hi>Tongues,</hi> and of the <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral Arts and and Sciences,</hi> thereby to make them <hi>uſefull</hi> and <hi>ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable</hi> to the <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> if they will ſtand upon <hi>this account,</hi> which is the <hi>ſureſt</hi> and <hi>ſafeſt</hi> Account they can ſtand on, and will be <hi>content</hi> to <hi>ſhake hands</hi> with their <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> and <hi>Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118325:19"/>
Intereſt,</hi> then let them ſtand, during the <hi>good Pleaſure</hi> of God; but if they will ſtill <hi>exalt</hi> themſelves <hi>above</hi> themſelves, and place <hi>themſelves</hi> on Chriſts very <hi>Throne,</hi> as <hi>if they had aſcended up on high to lead captivity captive, and to give gifts to men for the work of the Miniſtry,</hi> and ſo will <hi>preſume</hi> to darken the Glory of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>true Miniſtry</hi> which <hi>He</hi> ſends forth, as his <hi>Father</hi> ſent <hi>Him,</hi> then let them in the <hi>Name of Chriſt</hi> deſcend into that <hi>darkneſs</hi> out of which they <hi>firſt</hi> ſprang, that the <hi>Glory</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> may <hi>fill</hi> the World.</p>
               <p>And thus have I declared how the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> are offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> and <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> and ſo conſequently at all his things.</p>
               <p>And now I proceed to the <hi>third General</hi> I propounded; to wit, to ſhew</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="point">
               <head>3. Point.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>How great an evil it is to be thus offended at Chriſt and his Things.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The third General. To be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at Chriſt. 1. Its a ſign men are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of Chriſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And this appears in many particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>One Evil</hi> is, That to be <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>his</hi> Things, is a <hi>certain Evidence</hi> that men are wholly <hi>Ignorant</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and of <hi>God,</hi> though they be <hi>called</hi> Chriſtians, and have the <hi>Name</hi> of God alwayes in their mouths: For if men <hi>knew</hi> Chriſt <hi>aright,</hi> and <hi>God</hi> in Chriſt, it were <hi>impoſſible</hi> they ſhould be <hi>offended</hi> at Him; and inaſmuch as they <hi>are</hi> offended, it is <hi>certain</hi> they do not <hi>know</hi> Him by any <hi>revelation</hi> from the <hi>Father.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells his Diſciples, <hi>Joh.</hi> 16. 3. that the <hi>chief ground</hi> of that <hi>offence</hi> which the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> ſhould take againſt them who are his true <hi>Members,</hi> and have received the ſame <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> with him through true <hi>faith,</hi> is, <hi>becauſe they have not known the Father nor Him.</hi> For he that knows <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> is not <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>them;</hi> and he that knows <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is not offended at <hi>Him:</hi> But they that are offended at <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> know not <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and they that are offended at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> know not <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. When men are <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>his</hi> things, it is a <hi>ſign</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. That they are Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers.</note> they are real <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers,</hi> what ever <hi>forms</hi> of <hi>Godlineſs</hi> they may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:118325:19"/>
live under, and though it may be they have been <hi>old Profeſſors:</hi> for <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſt is precious to them that believe;</hi> wherefore they that are <hi>offended,</hi> are <hi>deſtitute</hi> of Faith.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They that are <hi>offended</hi> at Chriſt, <hi>loſe</hi> all that <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>eternal advantage</hi> that comes by <hi>Chriſt</hi> to true believers, and ſo <note place="margin">3. They looſe all advantage by Chriſt.</note> fall ſhort of the <hi>Love</hi> of God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>Reconciliation</hi> with God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of the <hi>Righteouſneſs, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and of all the <hi>fulneſs</hi> of God in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>eternal Redemption</hi> from the <hi>Law, Sin, Death,</hi> and <hi>Hell</hi> by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and of all that <hi>great Salvation</hi> that is in and by <hi>Him;</hi> And <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is wholly in <hi>vain</hi> to them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When men are <hi>fully</hi> and <hi>irreconcileably</hi> offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">4. Are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates.</note> and <hi>his</hi> things, it is a <hi>Sign</hi> they are of the <hi>wicked one,</hi> of the <hi>ſeed of the Serpent,</hi> and very <hi>Reprobates;</hi> as Chriſt told ſuch offended <hi>Iews; Ye are of your Father the Devil; and my ſheep hear my voice; but you hear it not</hi> (but are offended) <hi>and therefore you are none of my ſheep,</hi> that is, <hi>none</hi> of the <hi>Elect:</hi> And again ſaith <hi>Chriſt, all that my Father giveth me, ſhall come to me;</hi> Wherefore they that <hi>come</hi> not to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but are <hi>offended</hi> at him, are not <hi>given</hi> to him of <hi>God,</hi> and conſequently are <hi>Reprobates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. They that are <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are <hi>utterly ruined</hi> through <note place="margin">5. Are utterly ruined.</note> ſuch offence: Wherefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> is called <hi>a ſtone of ſtumbling, and rock of offence to them that are diſobedient and ſtumble at the Word;</hi> And he is ſaid <hi>to be ſet for the fall and ruine of many in Iſrael;</hi> and <hi>Mat.</hi> 21. 44. Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall fall on this ſtone, ſhall be broken; but on whoſoever it ſhall fall, it ſhall grinde him to pouder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For whoever <hi>ſtumbles,</hi> or <hi>daſhes</hi> againſt <hi>this</hi> Stone, daſhes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>God himſelf</hi> in the nature of <hi>Man:</hi> He daſhes againſt the <hi>Councel</hi> and <hi>Decree</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> againſt the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> againſt the Love, Mercy, Righteouſneſs, Truth, and Power of <hi>God;</hi> againſt the eternal Word and Spirit of <hi>God;</hi> and no man <hi>periſhes</hi> like <hi>that</hi> man: For he incurrs <hi>all</hi> that Wrath, Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, Deſtruction, Damnation, which the <hi>Lord God</hi> himſelf in all his <hi>infinite</hi> VViſdom, Knowledge, Righteouſneſs, Juſtice, and Power, can <hi>inflict</hi> on him to <hi>all eternity,</hi> and ſo he is indeed <hi>ground to pouder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea <hi>farther,</hi> that man that <hi>ſtumbles</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is not only <note place="margin">Ruined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remedy.</note> 
                  <hi>ruined</hi> by ſuch offence, but ruined without all <hi>means</hi> or <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery:</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:118325:20"/>
They that are <hi>broken</hi> againſt Him, and by Him, are bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in pieces like a <hi>potters veſſel,</hi> which can never be made up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; They that <hi>fall</hi> againſt Him, never riſe again; they that are <hi>ruined</hi> by him, are never <hi>repaired</hi> again. If a man were <hi>daſhed</hi> in pieces by <hi>Moſes,</hi> he might be <hi>repaired</hi> again by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but he that is <hi>deſtroyed</hi> by the <hi>Saviour,</hi> by whom ſhall he be ſaved? He that was condemned by the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God for Sin, might <hi>recover</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by the <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Mercy</hi> of God in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> But he that is <hi>deſtroyed</hi> by the Love and Mercy of God, is paſt all <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Remedy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore I intreat you to <hi>conſider</hi> this thing with <hi>all</hi> your hearts; For <hi>nothing</hi> makes ſuch <hi>ruines</hi> in the world as <hi>this Sin, Mens being offended againſt Chriſt and his Goſpel.</hi> This is the ſin that ruined <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> of old, and <hi>Germany</hi> of late; and if any thing undo this <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> this will undo it, the offence that is taken by <hi>mean men,</hi> and by men in <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>this</hi> is the ſin alſo that is like to <hi>undo</hi> and <hi>ruine</hi> the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity,</hi> and to race it down to the very ground, even your <hi>horrible</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">The Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty admoniſhed.</note> 
                  <hi>Envy, Enmity,</hi> and <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to the truth of the Goſpel: When <hi>Chriſts word,</hi> or the <hi>Truth</hi> as it is in <hi>Ieſus,</hi> is hated, oppoſed, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided, and ſcoffed at in your <hi>Colledges,</hi> in your <hi>Schools,</hi> in your <hi>Meetings,</hi> yea ſometimes in your <hi>Pulpits,</hi> this ſin will <hi>daſh</hi> you in <hi>pieces,</hi> that you ſhall find none to <hi>recover</hi> you. This ſin will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage againſt you <hi>the Son of the living God;</hi> and when <hi>his wrath</hi> is kindled againſt you not a <hi>little,</hi> but to the very <hi>utmoſt,</hi> for ſo great wickedneſs, ſhall then your <note n="*" place="margin">Certum eſt, Ariſtotelem mortuum &amp; damnatum, eſſe Doctorem ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die omnium <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitatum magis quàm Chriſtum. <hi>Luth. Reſponſ. ad Libr. Ambroſ. Cathar.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Maſters, Plato, Ariſtotle, Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>wretched Heathens,</hi> who with <hi>all</hi> their <hi>wiſdom</hi> knew not <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but are <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>damned,</hi> many hundred years ago be able to <hi>deliver</hi> you? Or ſhall <hi>Thomas,</hi> and <hi>Scotus,</hi> and other Schoolmen with their <hi>cold, vain,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Divinity help you? Or ſhall the <hi>Secular Arm,</hi> and <hi>worldly Power</hi> (whom you have ſeduced for many Ages) be able to <hi>ſhelter</hi> you in ſuch an <hi>hour?</hi> No certainly; but if you <hi>continue</hi> in your <hi>bitter Emnity</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>true</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Word and Goſpel of Chriſt, <hi>Chriſt lives and reignes to bring you down wonderfully,</hi> and to make your <hi>Name</hi> a <hi>ſhame</hi> and a <hi>Curſe</hi> to the whole <hi>true</hi> Church of God.</p>
               <p>And this poor <hi>contemptible Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> which you hear
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118325:20"/>
                  <hi>to day,</hi> and (it may be) moſt of you <hi>deſpiſe</hi> and eſteem of no more then a <hi>ſtraw</hi> for <hi>ſtrength,</hi> this very <hi>Word</hi> ſhall <hi>prevail</hi> againſt you, and <hi>triumph</hi> over you: And the poor <hi>People</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> that <hi>ſmall handfull</hi> of believers that are amongſt you, whom you <hi>deſpiſe</hi> in your <hi>hearts,</hi> and reckon but as the <hi>filth</hi> and <hi>off-ſcouring</hi> of the place, even <hi>they</hi> ſhall ſee your <hi>downfall,</hi> and ſhall ſay, <hi>Thou art righteous O Lord, who haſt judged thus,</hi> and ſhall ſay again, <hi>Even ſo Lord God almighty, true and righteous are thy Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And this now have I ſpoken in <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> to <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> and <note place="margin">The Concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</note> in <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> to his <hi>true Church,</hi> and in <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> alſo to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> that they might hear and avoid that <hi>Ruine</hi> with will otherwiſe <hi>inevitably</hi> befall them for their offence at Chriſt and his Goſpel. And now let them that <hi>can</hi> receive it, <hi>receive</hi> it, and let them that <hi>cannot, deride</hi> and <hi>reject</hi> it; But whether you <hi>receive</hi> it, or whether you <hi>reject</hi> it, <hi>ſure</hi> I am I have ſpoken the <hi>Truth,</hi> which <hi>God</hi> himſelf in his <hi>due</hi> time will <hi>witneſs</hi> to: and ſo much alſo for this Point.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="point">
               <head>The fourth Point, is, <note place="margin">4. Generall.</note>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>The bleſſedneſs of them that-are not offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> according <note place="margin">The Bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe who are not offended.</note> to Chriſts word here,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed is he whoſoever ſhall not be offended in me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now thoſe <hi>very few</hi> that are not <hi>offended</hi> at Chriſt and his <hi>things,</hi> when the whole <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly</hi> Church are offended, their <hi>Bleſſedneſs</hi> appears in <hi>many</hi> particulars.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As firſt, in that its <hi>evident</hi> that <hi>they all are taught of God,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Such are taught of God.</note> 
                  <hi>and have heard and learned from the Father</hi> himſelf touching the <hi>Son;</hi> And they that ſee Chriſt by the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> are not at all <hi>offended</hi> at him, when all <hi>other</hi> men are. For ſuch do clearly <hi>ſee</hi> Chriſts <hi>Power</hi> in his <hi>weakneſs;</hi> his <hi>Glory</hi> in his <hi>Reproach;</hi> his <hi>Exaltation</hi> in his <hi>Abaſement:</hi> his <hi>Divine</hi> nature in his <hi>Humane;</hi> they ſee his <hi>Sufferings</hi> were for our <hi>ſins,</hi> his <hi>ſtripes</hi> to <hi>heal</hi> Us, his <hi>Death</hi> to <hi>deliver</hi> us from death; and <hi>all</hi> this they <hi>know</hi> not only by the <hi>Letter</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>Father</hi> in their hearts, and ſo they cannot be <hi>offended</hi> at Chriſt, who ſee him <hi>thus.</hi> Wherefore when the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> had many <hi>ſeveral</hi> Opinions of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> notwithſtanding acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118325:21"/>
him to be <hi>the Son of the living God,</hi> Chriſt replied, <hi>bleſſed art thou Simon; for fleſh and blood hath not revealed this to thee, but my Father which is in Heaven:</hi> and this is thy <hi>bleſſedneſs,</hi> that thou <hi>knoweſt</hi> me by the <hi>Revelation of the Father,</hi> and ſo knoweſt me <hi>aright,</hi> and art not <hi>offended.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He then that is not <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt</hi> when all <hi>other</hi> men are, hath for <hi>certain</hi> the <hi>Fathers Teaching,</hi> and ſees <hi>Chriſt</hi> far <hi>otherwiſe</hi> then the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> do; He ſees <hi>Chriſt</hi> in all his <hi>Myſterie,</hi> and in all his <hi>Glory;</hi> and when we ſee him <hi>thus,</hi> we <hi>value</hi> him never the <hi>worſe</hi> for the <hi>form of a Servant,</hi> nor for all his <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches</hi> and <hi>ſufferings</hi> from the <hi>World,</hi> but we <hi>rather</hi> behold theſe things with the <hi>greater wonder</hi> and <hi>comfort;</hi> ſeeing for <hi>our ſakes</hi> he humbled himſelf from the <hi>form</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> to the <hi>form</hi> of a <hi>ſervant,</hi> and in that form to the <hi>death</hi> of the <hi>Croſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. They are <hi>bleſſed,</hi> becauſe through <hi>this Revelation</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> they have <hi>true Faith</hi> in Chriſt wrought in them. For <hi>true</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Through this Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on have true Faith.</note> 
                  <hi>Faith</hi> in Chriſt doth <hi>neceſſarily</hi> follow the <hi>Fathers Revelation;</hi> and when <hi>God</hi> teaches us <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we muſt needs believe in him; and through this <hi>Faith</hi> we know him by <hi>Experience:</hi> and he that knows <hi>Chriſt</hi> through the <hi>Experience</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> finds and feels <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be <hi>all that</hi> to him, which the <hi>Scripture</hi> ſpeaks of him: He through <hi>this faith</hi> feels <hi>Chriſt</hi> to be made unto him of <hi>God VViſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification, and Redemption,</hi> and <hi>all things;</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> being through <hi>Faith</hi> made <hi>all</hi> that to <hi>him,</hi> which he is in <hi>Himſelf,</hi> it is not <hi>poſſible</hi> he ſhould be <hi>offended</hi> at him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Farther,</hi> through this <hi>Experience</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> Chriſt becomes <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious</hi> to him, as <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet. 2. 7. to you who believe he is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious:</hi> That very <hi>Chriſt,</hi> which to <hi>others</hi> is a <hi>Stone of ſtumbling, and a rock of offence,</hi> is <hi>precious</hi> to them who have <hi>Faith,</hi> and know him by <hi>Experience;</hi> So <hi>precious</hi> that they eſteem all the <hi>greateſt</hi> and moſt <hi>excellent</hi> things in the world but <hi>droſs</hi> and <hi>dung</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of Him: and <hi>ſuch</hi> believers have choſen to part with their <hi>Liberty,</hi> their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> their <hi>Relations,</hi> and their own <hi>Lives,</hi> all which are <hi>precious</hi> things in <hi>themſelves,</hi> rather then they would part with this <hi>infinitely</hi> more <hi>precious Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They are <hi>bleſſed</hi> in that through <hi>this faith</hi> they have <hi>eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as Chriſt ſaith, <hi>on this rock I will build my Church:</hi> And he <note place="margin">3. Through this faith have eſtabliſhment.</note> that hath <hi>Chriſt</hi> for his only <hi>Foundation,</hi> is never <hi>offended</hi> at him,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118325:21"/>
what ever ſcandals the <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> raiſe up againſt him: But he that hath <hi>another</hi> Foundation then <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to wit, either his own <hi>works</hi> and <hi>Righteouſneſs,</hi> or the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Things</hi> of the World, when <hi>ſcandals</hi> come, they are preſently <hi>offended,</hi> and their <hi>offence</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt</hi> declares they are not <hi>built</hi> on him. But they whom <hi>nothing</hi> can offend, they are ſurely <hi>built</hi> and <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> on Chriſt, and in this they are <hi>bleſſed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. They who have received the <hi>Revelation</hi> of the <hi>Father,</hi> and <note place="margin">4. Through this eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are free from periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> through this Revelation, <hi>true Faith,</hi> and through this true Faith, <hi>firm Eſtabliſhment,</hi> are <hi>farther</hi> Bleſſed, in that all ſuch are <hi>paſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing;</hi> For he that cleaves ſo <hi>inſeparably</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> that nothing can <hi>offend</hi> him, and is ſo firmly <hi>built</hi> on Chriſt that nothing can <hi>remove</hi> him; It is impoſſible for him to <hi>periſh</hi> by <hi>any thing:</hi> Wherefore it is ſaid, <hi>behold I lay in Sion a chief corner ſtone, Elect and precious, and he that believeth on him ſhall not be confounded:</hi> And <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. ſaith Chriſt, <hi>On this rock I will build my Church, and the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. And laſt of all, They that have eſcaped the <hi>Offence</hi> of Chriſt, are <hi>ſure of Salvation:</hi> For ſuch do truly partake of all that <hi>infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">5. Are ſure of Salvation.</note> and <hi>everlaſting advantage</hi> that is by <hi>Chriſt;</hi> they partake of his <hi>own</hi> Righteouſneſs, and Wiſdom, and Truth, and Power, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Life, and Word, and Spirit, and of <hi>all</hi> his <hi>fulneſs,</hi> and thus they have true <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of the beginnings of <hi>eternal life,</hi> as <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>Theſe things have I written to you that believe, that you may know ye have eternal life abiding in you. 1 Joh.</hi> 5. 13. and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>I give unto my ſheep eternal life;</hi> that very <hi>life</hi> which was in the <hi>Father,</hi> and was communicated to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and manifeſted in his <hi>humane Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in <hi>all</hi> theſe <hi>Regards</hi> are they <hi>bleſſed</hi> that are not <hi>offended</hi> at Chriſt, as Chriſt affirms, <hi>bleſſed is he whoſoever ſhall not be offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in me.</hi> And ſo now I proceed to ſome Uſes. <note place="margin">5. <hi>General.</hi> The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="point">
               <head>5. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſes.</head>
               <p n="1">1. To <hi>warn</hi> all of all men ſorts, that they take <hi>ſpecial care</hi> that they <note place="margin">1. To admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh men to take heed that themſelves be not offended at Chriſt.</note> be not <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>things</hi> of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> You have heard that the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>wiſeſt,</hi> and <hi>greateſt</hi> of the world, and that the <hi>worldly Church,</hi> and the <hi>holieſt</hi> and moſt <hi>religious</hi> in that are offended at <hi>Chriſt;</hi> And you have heard alſo how <hi>great an evil</hi> it is to be offended, and how <hi>great a bleſſedneſs</hi> it is not to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended; Wherefore I do <hi>adviſe</hi> you from the <hi>Word,</hi> to <hi>take care</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:118325:22"/>
that <hi>you</hi> be not found amongſt <hi>them</hi> who are <hi>offended</hi> at Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Objection. </seg>
                  </label> But you will be ready to ſay, <hi>We hope we are not offended at Chriſt, but we do love, honor, and embrace both Chriſt and the things of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer </seg>
                  </label> To this I anſwer, That <hi>many</hi> do uſually ſay they are not offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed<note place="margin">Many are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at Chriſt, who ſay they are not offended. 1. They that are offended at the Word, are offended at Chriſt.</note> at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and it may be ſome may <hi>think</hi> ſo too, who yet <hi>indeed</hi> and <hi>before</hi> the <hi>Lord</hi> are <hi>grievouſly</hi> offended at Him: as may <hi>thus</hi> appears For.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt, He that is offended at the <hi>true Word</hi> of Chriſt, is offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf: For <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Word,</hi> the <hi>Goſpel Word,</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> that was <hi>with God,</hi> and <hi>was God,</hi> and came into the <hi>fleſh,</hi> and that <hi>ſpake,</hi> and <hi>did,</hi> and <hi>ſuffered,</hi> and <hi>overcame</hi> all in that fleſh; and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaid it was <hi>expedient</hi> for the <hi>Church,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>withdraw</hi> his <hi>fleſh</hi> or <hi>bodily</hi> preſence, and only <hi>continue</hi> that preſence of his with them which is by the <hi>living Word of God</hi> through the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> And this is that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> who is <hi>preſent with believers to the end of the World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo he that is <hi>offended</hi> at the true <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Word held forth by the <hi>confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> is offended at <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> who is <hi>preſent</hi> in <hi>that</hi> Word; Wherefore ſaith <hi>Peter, 1 Pet. 2. 8. He is a ſtone of ſtumbling and rock of offence to them that Stumble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the Word.</hi> The <hi>moſt</hi> people adore the <hi>outward name</hi> of Chriſt, but yet cannot endure the <hi>true Word</hi> of Chriſt. Now all that are <hi>offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> at the true <hi>ſpiritual</hi> Word of Chriſt, and <hi>right Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> are offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and <hi>ſtumble at that ſtumbling Stone.</hi> And thus <hi>multitudes</hi> are offended at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who do <hi>think</hi> themſelves very <hi>free</hi> from this ſin.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They that are offended at <hi>true Believers,</hi> are offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. And they who are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at true Believers.</note> 
                  <hi>himſelf.</hi> For <hi>they</hi> are in the <hi>World</hi> as <hi>He</hi> was, and <hi>Walk</hi> as <hi>He</hi> did <hi>Walk;</hi> And they are <hi>one fleſh</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> with him; They are his <hi>Members,</hi> They are <hi>Himſelf;</hi> And whoſoever is offended at <hi>Them,</hi> is offended at <hi>Him.</hi> For <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>ſelf ſame</hi> both in <hi>Himſelf</hi> the <hi>Head,</hi> and in <hi>Believers</hi> his <hi>Members.</hi> And <hi>Theſe</hi> are the <hi>Children</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> together with <hi>Him</hi> the <hi>firſt born,</hi> and <hi>Theſe</hi> are comprehended in the ſame <hi>Love, choſen</hi> with the ſame <hi>Choice, called</hi> with the ſame <hi>Calling, Sanctified</hi> with the ſame <hi>Holineſs, Kept</hi> by the ſame <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Glorified</hi> with the ſame <hi>Glory; Theſe</hi> partake of the ſame <hi>Divine Nature,</hi> and have the <hi>ſame Word</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> dwelling in them, in the <hi>ſame</hi> Righteouſneſs, Wiſdom,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118325:22"/>
Grace and Truth, and there is no <hi>difference</hi> between <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>them,</hi> but what is between the <hi>Head</hi> and the <hi>Members,</hi> the <hi>firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born</hi> and his <hi>Brethren.</hi> And ſo, they that are <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Theſe,</hi> would as <hi>certainly</hi> and <hi>neceſſarily</hi> be offended at <hi>Chriſt himſelf,</hi> if <hi>He</hi> had lived in <hi>their</hi> time, or if <hi>They</hi> had lived in <hi>his</hi> time.</p>
               <p>It is <hi>manifeſt</hi> then that They who are <hi>offended</hi> at the <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and at the <hi>Works</hi> of Chriſt, at the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> of Chriſt in <hi>Believers,</hi> would have been offended at them in <hi>Chriſt Himſelf:</hi> Yea, they who are offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Believers,</hi> would <hi>much more</hi> have been offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Himſelf;</hi> becauſe what is in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> but in <hi>part,</hi> was <hi>fully</hi> in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> And what is in a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> in a <hi>ſmall meaſure,</hi> was in Chriſt <hi>without meaſure;</hi> and there was in <hi>Chriſt</hi> a far more <hi>glorious preſence</hi> and <hi>manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> then in <hi>any Chriſtian;</hi> and <hi>proportionably</hi> would they have been <hi>offended</hi> at <hi>Him</hi> in <hi>Himſelf,</hi> who are truly offended at <hi>Him</hi> in his <hi>Members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. They who are <hi>offended</hi> at the <hi>Sufferings</hi> which come on <note place="margin">3. And they who are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at the ſufferings of Chriſtians.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſtians</hi> for <hi>Chriſts ſake,</hi> are offended at <hi>Chriſt Himſelf,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſuffer not on their <hi>own account</hi> but on <hi>Chriſts,</hi> and the <hi>Croſs</hi> they take up and bear is <hi>His,</hi> and not their <hi>own.</hi> If They would <hi>live</hi> as other men in the <hi>common Religion</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> and make uſe of the <hi>form of Godlineſs</hi> without the <hi>Power;</hi> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with that <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> which the <hi>Clergy</hi> ſhall allow for <hi>Orthodox,</hi> and the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> accordingly <hi>approve</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm:</hi> then might they live as <hi>quietly</hi> and <hi>proſperouſly</hi> as other men: but becauſe they cleave only to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and take <hi>Him</hi> for their <hi>only</hi> Maſter in the things of <hi>God,</hi> and do receive his <hi>Word</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> and then <hi>hold</hi> it forth to <hi>others,</hi> therefore the <hi>World hates them,</hi> as Chriſt ſaid, <hi>I have given them thy Word, and the world hath hated them, becauſe they are not of the world, as I am not of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore every <hi>true Chriſtian</hi> who ſpeaks and profeſſes the <hi>VVord</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> the <hi>VVord</hi> which exalts <hi>Chriſt</hi> alone and his <hi>things,</hi> and <hi>throws down</hi> all other things of the <hi>VVorld,</hi> though in the higheſt eſteem with men, muſt needs meet with his <hi>enemies</hi> and <hi>avengers,</hi> his <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> his <hi>Herods</hi> and <hi>Pilates:</hi> And now when the <hi>carnal Church</hi> which hath the favor and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the <hi>State,</hi> ſees poor Chriſtians for the <hi>VVords</hi> ſake <hi>ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> all the hatred, malice and rage of the <hi>world</hi> and <hi>worldly</hi> Church, they are greatly <hi>offended</hi> at them; and in being offended
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118325:23"/>
at <hi>them,</hi> they are offended at <hi>Chriſt Himſelf;</hi> for it is <hi>his cauſe</hi> in which they <hi>ſuffer,</hi> and not their <hi>own,</hi> and it is <hi>he</hi> who <hi>ſuffers</hi> in his cauſe more then <hi>they,</hi> as is evident by that <hi>complaint</hi> of his, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſecutest thou me?</hi> I ſay, as it is <hi>Christ,</hi> that <hi>is,</hi> and <hi>doth</hi> all in his <hi>true Saints,</hi> ſo alſo it is <hi>he</hi> that <hi>ſuffers</hi> all in them; and they who are <hi>offended</hi> at theſe <hi>Sufferings</hi> of <hi>Believers</hi> which they ſuffer in and for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are offended at <hi>Chriſt himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in theſe <hi>three regards</hi> it doth plainly appear that many who pretend to honor the <hi>outward Name</hi> of Chriſt, are yet indeed <hi>grievouſly offended</hi> at Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> 2. The <hi>ſecond <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> is another <hi>Caution</hi> to <hi>warn</hi> all men to <hi>take heed,</hi> as not to be offended <hi>themſelves</hi> at <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo alſo not to be <note place="margin">Caution, not to be offended through the offences of others, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, 1. That it is no new thing for men to be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended at Chriſt.</note> 
                  <hi>troubled</hi> nor <hi>offended</hi> with the <hi>offences</hi> of <hi>Others:</hi> But when we ſee the <hi>whole world</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> offended at Chriſt and his things, let us <hi>take care</hi> that we be not <hi>therefore</hi> offended alſo, but let us <hi>conſider.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. That it is no <hi>new thing</hi> that Chriſt and his <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſhould be ſtumbled at, and <hi>contradicted</hi> by the World and worldly Church; For thus it was <hi>foretold</hi> by the <hi>Prophets,</hi> and thus it hath been <hi>done</hi> ever ſince Chriſt was manifeſted in the <hi>fleſh.</hi> In the days of his Miniſtry, his <hi>Doctrine</hi> was ſo <hi>contrary</hi> to carnal reaſon and the humane apprehenſions of <hi>men</hi> in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> that many of his <hi>Diſciples</hi> ſaid, <hi>This is a hard ſaying, who can bear it?</hi> Joh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 6. Yea <hi>many of his Diſciples murmured at his Doctrine, and went back and walked no more with him;</hi> And all along during <hi>Chriſts</hi> Miniſtry, many were ſnared, and ſtumbled, and fell, and were broken <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by:</hi> and he that is <hi>troubled</hi> and <hi>offended</hi> at this, muſt get him <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother</hi> Chriſt, and <hi>another</hi> Goſpel; For the <hi>true</hi> Chriſt is ſet for a <hi>ſign to be ſpoken against,</hi> &amp; the <hi>true Goſpel</hi> is ſet for a <hi>Word of contention</hi> and <hi>contradiction</hi> to the <hi>carnal</hi> Chriſtians, &amp; to the <hi>whole VVorld.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore when we ſee in our time the <hi>VVorld</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> offended at Chriſt and his Goſpel, let us know that <hi>thus</hi> it hath been from the <hi>beginning;</hi> and let u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know that as Chriſt and his Goſpel are the <hi>ſame</hi> now as they were <hi>then,</hi> ſo the <hi>VVorld</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Devil,</hi> the Head of both, are the <hi>ſame</hi> alſo; and therefore it cannot be but <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel</hi> muſt ſuffer the <hi>ſame</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Chriſt and his Word are not the worſe for the offence of the World.</note> contradiction in <hi>our</hi> time, as they have done in all <hi>former</hi> times.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That we may not be <hi>offended</hi> with the <hi>common</hi> and <hi>general</hi> offence of <hi>others,</hi> let us conſider that <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel</hi> are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118325:23"/>
the <hi>worſe</hi> for the offence which the <hi>World</hi> takes at them, but <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſtill the <hi>Son of the living God,</hi> and the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is ſtill the <hi>Power of God to Salvation,</hi> to every one that believes, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Word</hi> do ſtill remain a <hi>ſure foundation</hi> for the <hi>true</hi> Church of God; That Chriſt crucified, which is to the <hi>Jews</hi> a ſtumbling block, and to the <hi>Greeks</hi> fooliſhneſs, is notwithſtanding to them who <hi>believe, Chriſt the Power of God, and Chriſt the Wiſdom of God. 1 Cor.</hi> 1. So that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is not the <hi>worſe</hi> for the Worlds being offended at Him, neither do the <hi>faithfull</hi> think him the <hi>worſe:</hi> Nay the more <hi>vile</hi> he is to <hi>others,</hi> he is ſtill the more <hi>precius</hi> to <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Let us <hi>conſider</hi> that notwithſtanding all the <hi>offence</hi> of men, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Goſpel</hi> ſtill <hi>remain</hi> and <hi>continue</hi> what they are, and <note place="margin">3. Chriſt ſtill remains, for al ſuch offence.</note> cannot be <hi>prevailed</hi> againſt. Men may be <hi>offended</hi> at Chriſt and his Word, but they canot <hi>deſtroy</hi> and <hi>extinguiſh</hi> them, but they ſtill <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> and do alwayes <hi>prevail</hi> againſt all things that oppoſe them.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, to deliver us from the <hi>ſcandal</hi> of <hi>all</hi> Mens being <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended</hi> againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we are to <hi>conſider,</hi> that as <hi>all</hi> the <hi>World</hi> have been, <hi>are</hi> and <hi>will</hi> be againſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſhall <hi>riſe</hi> up and <hi>increaſe</hi> againſt all the <hi>World,</hi> and againſt all their <hi>thoughts</hi> and <hi>endeavours;</hi> And all their <hi>Councels, Contrivances,</hi> and induſtrious <hi>Actings</hi> ſhall not be able to <hi>hinder</hi> the Kingdom of <hi>Chriſt</hi> from <hi>proſpering</hi> and growing <hi>great;</hi> But it ſhall <hi>ariſe</hi> and <hi>ſtand up</hi> in all its <hi>Glory,</hi> out of the <hi>midſt</hi> of all the <hi>offences</hi> and <hi>contradictions</hi> in the world. Wherefore <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom</hi> are called <hi>a Tried ſtone;</hi> for he hath <hi>long ago</hi> indured whatever the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>worldly Church</hi> could do againſt Him, and whatever the <hi>might</hi> and <hi>malice</hi> of <hi>men</hi> and <hi>Devils</hi> could do againſt him, and yet hath <hi>overcome</hi> all: <hi>All</hi> that have <hi>oppoſed</hi> Him have been <hi>daſhed</hi> in <hi>pieces</hi> by him, in the <hi>ſeveral</hi> Ages of the World; and <hi>He</hi> and his <hi>Kingdom</hi> ſtill <hi>remain,</hi> and ſhall remain for <hi>ever;</hi> For He is a <hi>ſure tried ſtone.</hi> And <hi>they</hi> in this <hi>Town</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> who are the moſt grievouſly offended at the <hi>Word,</hi> ſhall not by <hi>all</hi> their ſubtilty, Malice, Slanders, evil ſpeaking, nor by <hi>any thing</hi> they can <hi>ſay</hi> or <hi>do, deſign</hi> or <hi>undertake,</hi> be able to <hi>prevail</hi> againſt it, but they muſt ſhortly <hi>die</hi> and <hi>depart</hi> out of the <hi>World,</hi> and in <hi>deſpite</hi> of them, leave this <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God</hi> behind them, to <hi>live,</hi> and <hi>flouriſh,</hi> and <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread</hi> the World. And theſe <hi>conſiderations,</hi> if entertained by <hi>Faith,</hi> may keep us from being <hi>offended</hi> at the <hi>offence</hi> of the <hi>whole World:</hi> And this for the ſecond Uſe.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:118325:24"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>3</label> 3. In the <hi>third place,</hi> I ſhall ſhew you how <hi>believers</hi> ought to <note place="margin">Direction, how to carry our ſelves in the midſt of offences. 1. To abide in Chriſt.</note> 
                  <hi>carry</hi> themſelves in the midſt of thoſe <hi>offences</hi> that are taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and againſt <hi>themſelves</hi> for Chriſts <hi>ſake,</hi> that is, for his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Doctrines</hi> ſake.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Firſt then, We ought to be careful to <hi>abide</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to <hi>walk</hi> in Chriſt; To <hi>ſpeak</hi> all our words, and to <hi>do</hi> all our <hi>works,</hi> and to <hi>live</hi> our whole <hi>life</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and in his <hi>Spirit,</hi> that ſo the <hi>World</hi> may not be offended at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> who <hi>are</hi> nothing, and <hi>do</hi> nothing in <hi>our ſelves,</hi> but at <hi>Chriſt</hi> in Us, who <hi>is</hi> and <hi>doth</hi> all in us: And then as <hi>we</hi> ſhall certainly be <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> and <hi>preſerved</hi> in Chriſt, through our abiding in him: ſo <hi>they</hi> ſhall as certainly <hi>periſh</hi> and be ruined through <hi>His</hi> abiding in Us, and their <hi>daſhing</hi> againſt <hi>Him</hi> in Us.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To carry our ſelves <hi>aright</hi> in the midſt of <hi>offences,</hi> let us be <hi>ſure</hi> that the <hi>Word</hi> we believe and hold forth is <hi>Chriſts Word,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. To be ſure the Word we confeſs is the true Word of God.</note> and then we may be very <hi>confident</hi> that this <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>cauſe</hi> ſhall and muſt <hi>remain,</hi> how many <hi>Adverſaries</hi> ſoever it may have; and though the <hi>World</hi> and <hi>Devil</hi> may <hi>rage</hi> againſt it, yet (as hath been ſaid) they ſhall never be able to <hi>overthrow</hi> it, much leſs to <hi>root</hi> it out.</p>
               <p>A <hi>true Chriſtian</hi> muſt be able to ſay, I know the <hi>Word</hi> which I <hi>believe</hi> and profeſs, is the <hi>only Word</hi> of the Lord God, and his <hi>everlaſting</hi> and <hi>unchangeable truth,</hi> and the <hi>laſt manifeſtation</hi> of his will by his own <hi>Son;</hi> and what ever Word <hi>agreeth</hi> not herewith, is <hi>falſe,</hi> and of the <hi>Devil,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt;</hi> and therefore by <hi>this</hi> Word will I <hi>ſtay,</hi> though <hi>all</hi> the <hi>VVorld</hi> be againſt me.</p>
               <p>And when we are thus <hi>certain</hi> of the Word of God through <hi>Faith</hi> and the <hi>Spirit,</hi> it <hi>comforts</hi> the heart and makes it <hi>glad,</hi> and <hi>ſettles</hi> it in <hi>inward Peace</hi> and <hi>Reſt,</hi> in the midſt of all <hi>outward Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions</hi> and <hi>Troubles<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> as through <hi>Gods</hi> goodneſs we have found by <hi>Experience.</hi> For when we know that the <hi>VVord</hi> which we have received and profeſs, is the very <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> then alſo we <hi>know</hi> that it ſhall prevail againſt all Kingdoms, Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths, States, Governments, Societies, Univerſities, againſt all Laws, Orders, Decrees, Acts, and againſt all ſorts and degrees of <hi>worldly</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Powers</hi> which are <hi>contrary</hi> thereunto, and ſhal in the time <hi>appointed</hi> by God utterly conſume them, and bring them to <hi>nothing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And by theſe <hi>Means,</hi> to wit, by <hi>abiding</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and being <hi>all</hi> in Him; And by being <hi>ſure</hi> that the <hi>Word</hi> we <hi>believe</hi> and profeſs is
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118325:24"/>
                  <hi>His</hi> Word, we may live <hi>ſafely</hi> in the midſt of all <hi>offences</hi> without the leaſt <hi>prejudice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>4</label> 4. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I ſhall ſpeak a <hi>few words</hi> to thoſe in this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> and <hi>Town</hi> who <hi>are offended</hi> at Chriſt and his <hi>Goſpel;</hi> and alſo a <hi>few words</hi> to <hi>thoſe</hi> who (through the Grace of God) have <hi>eſcaped</hi> this <hi>offence,</hi> and ſo ſhall <hi>conclude this</hi> matter.</p>
               <p>And firſt, for <hi>you</hi> who <hi>are offended</hi> at <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>VVord,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. A Word to them who are offended.</note> which (we muſt <hi>needs</hi> ſay) is <hi>come</hi> amongſt you in <hi>Truth,</hi> and in <hi>plainneſs,</hi> and are angry at it, and ſtorm at it, and reproach it, and think and contrive how to <hi>reſiſt</hi> it, and to <hi>hinder</hi> the free courſe and paſſage of it in this <hi>place,</hi> becauſe it is not only <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to the <hi>Philoſophical Divinity</hi> of the <hi>Schools</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity,</hi> and the common <hi>carnal Religion</hi> of the <hi>Nation,</hi> but doth alſo <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> and <hi>condemn</hi> them, and will have the <hi>haughtineſs of men bowed down,</hi> and the <hi>pride of men laid low,</hi> and the <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt and his things only exalted,</hi> and that <hi>here</hi> where the <hi>VVit,</hi> and <hi>VViſdom,</hi> and <hi>Parts,</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> and <hi>Accompliſhments</hi> of <hi>men,</hi> have ruffled it, and <hi>reigned</hi> hitherto. I ſay, <hi>you</hi> that are thus offended for this cauſe, are offended at <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, and at <hi>God</hi> in Chriſt, and you do <hi>ſtumble</hi> at the <hi>ſtumbling Stone,</hi> and ſhall ſo fall thereby, as to be <hi>broken in pieces;</hi> Yea this <hi>Stone it ſelf</hi> ſhall <hi>fall</hi> upon you, and ſhall <hi>grinde</hi> you to <hi>pouder,</hi> and you ſhall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed <hi>with everlaſting deſtruction</hi> from the preſence of the Lord, and from the Glory of his power, and <hi>this deſtruction</hi> ſhall be poured on you with the greateſt <hi>ſeverity</hi> and <hi>wrath,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf can inflict in all his <hi>Infiniteneſs</hi> and <hi>Eternity;</hi> For if (as the Penman of the <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſaith) <hi>the word ſpoken by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels was ſtedfaſt, and every trangreſſion and diſobedience received a juſt recompence of reward, what eſcaping can there be for them who neglect that great ſalvation, which was publiſhed at firſt by the Lord Chriſt, and after confirmed by the firſt believers, and witneſſed to by Signs and Miracles, and gifts of the Spirit, by God himſelf? Heb.</hi> 2. 2, 3. and if (as the ſame <hi>Believer</hi> ſaith) <hi>he that deſpiſed Moſes Law died without mercy, of how much ſorer puniſhment ſhall he be guilty who treads underfoot the Son of God? &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> it had been much <hi>better</hi> for you, that you had lived among the <hi>Heathen</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> where the <hi>Goſpel</hi> of God our Saviour had never been <hi>heard,</hi> then to hear this <hi>joyful ſound</hi> which manifeſts the <hi>Love</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and brings along with it <hi>Remiſſion</hi> of <hi>ſins</hi> and the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118325:25"/>
                  <hi>gift</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> through <hi>faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to be <hi>offended</hi> at it, and ſo to be <hi>deſtroyed</hi> by the <hi>word</hi> of <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and to be <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately</hi> puniſhed with <hi>eternal death</hi> by him who is the <hi>true God and eternal life.</hi> And this is the <hi>heavy burden</hi> which the <hi>VVord</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath laid on <hi>your</hi> ſhoulders, and you cannot <hi>remove</hi> it.</p>
               <p>2. And then for you <hi>true Believers,</hi> you <hi>little flock,</hi> you <hi>few choſen</hi> out of the <hi>many called,</hi> who <hi>hear</hi> the VVord of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <note place="margin">2. A Word to them who are not offended.</note> are <hi>not</hi> offended at it, though you hear it everywhere, and that with <hi>both</hi> ears in this <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> and <hi>Town,</hi> Contradicted, Miſre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported, Reproached, Scandalized, and called Error, Hereſie, New Light, Faction, Schiſm, Sedition, and hear all manner of <hi>evil</hi> ſpoken againſt it <hi>falſly,</hi> not only by the <hi>rude</hi> and <hi>ignorant</hi> People, but alſo by the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> and <hi>Hypocrites</hi> of this place, and yet for all theſe <hi>offences</hi> you are not <hi>offended</hi> at it, but own it, and love it, and imbrace it, notwithſtanding all the <hi>extream diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages</hi> it hath from this <hi>Place,</hi> which is counted by <hi>carnal people</hi> the very <hi>fountain</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> and the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> knowing by <hi>Gods</hi> own <hi>teaching,</hi> that it is the <hi>VVord</hi> of <hi>Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Life,</hi> and the <hi>Truth</hi> as it is in <hi>Ieſus,</hi> though contrary to the ſenſe of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſity</hi> and <hi>Schools,</hi> who have generally their teaching from man; To <hi>all ſuch,</hi> I ſay by the <hi>word</hi> of the <hi>Lord, bleſſed</hi> are ye, of the <hi>bleſſed</hi> of the <hi>Lord,</hi> for you are all <hi>taught</hi> of <hi>God</hi> touching Chriſt, and have heard and learned the <hi>Son</hi> from the <hi>Father,</hi> and through <hi>this teaching</hi> you have <hi>true faith</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and ſo know him by <hi>experience,</hi> whereupon Chriſt is moſt <hi>precious</hi> to you; and through this <hi>faith</hi> you are <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> on Chriſt, ſo that nothing from <hi>Earth</hi> or <hi>Hell</hi> can remove you: And being ſo <hi>eſtabliſhed</hi> through <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> with Chriſt, you can no more <hi>periſh</hi> then Chriſt can periſh, and you ſhall as ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tainly be <hi>ſaved</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ſaved.</p>
               <p>This is your <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> from the <hi>Lord;</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> and the <hi>Devil</hi> ſhall never be able to make it <hi>void;</hi> And <hi>therefore</hi> go and <hi>eat</hi> your <hi>bread</hi> with <hi>cheerfulneſs,</hi> and <hi>lie down</hi> and <hi>riſe</hi> and <hi>live</hi> in <hi>ſafety</hi> under the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of the <hi>Almighty,</hi> though in this <hi>World,</hi> and in this <hi>Place,</hi> you dwell among <hi>Bears</hi> and <hi>Lyons,</hi> and have your converſation in the midſt of <hi>Scorpions;</hi> for <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf hath bleſſed you in <hi>himſelf,</hi> and you ſhall be <hi>bleſſed for ever; Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he whoſoever ſhall not be offended in me.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
